斯坦福大学
Stanford University.
欢迎来到 2013 至 2014 秋季学期 CS193P
Okay. Well, welcome to CS193P fall of 2013/2014.
今天我们会继续讲解
Today we’re going to continue our discussion
属性化字符串的内容
of attributed string from last time
还会介绍 UITextView
and talk about UITextView,
它基本上是一个可变属性化字符串查看器
which is basically a mutable attributed string viewer, okay?
有点像 UILable 但是功能更强大
It’s kind of like a UILabel but much more powerful.
我们会讲讲这部分内容
And we’ll talk about that.
然后我们会介绍 iOS7 甚至整个 iOS 中
Then we’re going to talk about a very important kind of conceptual thing
非常重要的一个概念
in iOS 7, or in iOS in general,
也就是视图控制器生命周期
which is view controller lifecycle.
指的是 MVC 中控制器的生命周期
So that’s just the lifecycle of the controller part of your MVC
以及在其生命周期的各个阶段中
and how it gets notified at different times in its lifecycle
如何得到事件进展的通知
about what’s going on.
然后我们会讲解广播站机制
Then we’re going to talk about the radio station
在讲 MVC 时我提到过
that I referred to in MVC.
今天我们会从不太相同的角度进行讲解
We’re going to talk about it in a little different context that we see in MVC
因为目前我只是想为大家介绍一下这部分内容
because I just want to introduce it to you now.
而在今天的整个讲解过程中
And then throughout today’s thing –
我会… 看这个幻灯片
so I’m going to be — slides here.
在幻灯片讲解过程中
I’m going to be stopping every once and a while
我会停下来做一些演示
and we’ll do a little demo.
然后再继续讲解幻灯片内容
And then we will move back to the slides
如此反复 直至讲完全部内容
and back and forth as we cover various topics.
明白了吗 那我们先来讲 UITextView
Okay? So let’s start with UITextView.
和 UILabel 一样 它也能显示文本 但是功能更强大
Like UILabel in that it displays text but way more powerful
因为它能显示多行文本
because the text is multiline.
在 UILabel 中 如果想显示多行文本
UILabel, if you want it to be multiline,
你需要提前声明有多少行
you kind of have to say how many lines it is in advance,
而在 UITextView 中 想显示多少行都可以
whereas UITextView, as many lines as it needs.
还可以滚动 可以编辑 也可以根据需要选中
It’s also scrollable, editable, or just selectable if you want.
当然了 你还可以使用可变属性化字符串的各种设置
And of course, you get all the mutable attributed string
比如颜色等等
setting of various things like colors and all that stuff.
UITextView 非常强大且容易使用
So UITextView, super powerful object but very easy to use.
使用时要用到它的一个属性 叫做 textStorage
The way you use it is that it has a property called textStorage,
它是一个 NSTextStorage 类型
which is an NSTextStorage.
NSTextStorage 是 NSMutableAttributedString 的一个子类
NSTextStorage is a subclass of NSMutableAttributedString.
你得到这个 textStorage 后
So you get this textStorage,
就可以直接设置属性
and you can just start setting attributes
或者如果它是可编辑的 用户会进行编辑
or if it’s editable, the user will start editing it
属性会在这个可变字符串上显示出来
and the attributes will just show up on this mutable string.
这是 iOS7 中新增的一个很棒的编程接口
It’s a super great programming interface new in iOS 7.
它有一个可变属性化字符串
Okay. It’s having a mutable attributed string
像这样由 UITextView 发布出来
be just vended like this by UITextView
你或用户可以随时对其进行编辑
and editable on the fly by both the user and by you
这是新功能 非常棒 非常好用
is all new and it’s really incredibly awesome and easy to use.
UITextView 有一些方法
There are some methods on UITextView like, you know,
比如字体属性可以用来设置字体
property font where you can just set the font.
但是大家要明白 当你设置字体时
Understand, though, that when you set the font,
它会依次查看可变字符串中的每个字符
all it’s doing is going through every character in the mutable string
然后将字体属性名称
and setting the font attribute name –
设置为这个字体
font, you know, that thing — to this font.
要记得加粗和斜体都是字体的属性
So remember that bold and italic are attributes of the font.
大小其实也是
Okay? And so is the size, actually.
所以如果你调用这个设置字体方法
So if you call this method set font –
调用设置字体的 setter
you know, call the set font setter there –
所有加粗 斜体和大小的设置
it’s going to blast all of your bolds,
就会无效了
and italics, and size, okay?
所以使用时要小心
So you be a little careful of that.
如果你想设置所有字符的字体
If you want to set the font, though, of every character
且加粗斜体和大小不变
and have that stuff preserved,
只要加个 for 循环
just do a little for loop,
逐一查看可变字符串的全部属性
go through all the attributes in the mutable string,
得到当前字体
get the font that’s already there.
你可以用 UIFontDescriptor 的符号特征方法
You can grab the symbolic traits that are off of it
获取它的符号特征
using the symbolic traits method in UIFontDescriptor
然后新建一个字体
and then create a new font
等于你想要设置的字体加上那些特征
that is the font you’re trying to set, plus those traits,
然后再将最后结果设置为属性
and then set it back as the attribute.
这是实现它需要用到的 for 循环
So a little for loop there to do that.
但是我希望大家在用设置字体这类方法时要小心
But I just want you to be careful about methods like set font,
这类方法在设置字体属性时
which are going to set the font attribute
会改变全部字符的设置
of all the characters, okay?
UITextView 具有非常高级的文本布局机制
UITextView has incredibly advanced text layout mechanisms.
比如 你可以指定文本所处容器
For example, you can specify the container that the text is going to be in
甚至可以指定不可填充文本的限制区域
and it can even have exclusion zones.
所以如果你在文字中间放置一张图片
So if you had an image that was dropped in the middle of your text
想让文字环绕图片
and you wanted text to flow around it,
即便这张图片的形状很奇怪
even if it’s funny-shaped thing — you know, image –
你也可以实现文字环绕效果
you can flow around it.
你只要… 非常简单
And you just — it’s so easy to do it.
难以置信
unbelievably.
你只要创建一条贝塞尔曲线
You just create a Bezier path
包围住想要环绕的对象
that encompasses the thing you want it to flow around.
你只要在 UITextView 的 textContainer 属性中
You just set that as an exclusion zone
把它设为限制区域
in the textContainer property here of UITextView,
就会自动进行环绕布局
and it will just flow around.
我们这里不再讲这些高级应用了
So we’re not going to talk about that advanced stuff.
这些都是 TextKit 中的内容 是 iOS7 的新增功能
It’s all part of TextKit, which is new for iOS 7.
layoutManager 负责布局各个字形
The layoutManager is the thing that lays out the glyphs.
它得到全部字符和它们的属性
So it takes all the characters and all the attributes and stuff
然后对各个字形逐一进行布局
and it laying out the glyphs one by one.
有人不知道字形是什么吗
For those of you who don’t know what glyphs are,
它们代表一个或一串字符
they’re kind of how you represent a character or a sequence of characters
在屏幕上显示的样子
on screen with some things.
所以 layoutManager 负责
So the layoutManager is the thing
在文本容器中布局字形
that lays the glyphs out inside the text container.
所以如果你对字体排印感兴趣
So if you’re interested in typography
或者想在期末项目中
or you’re going to do a final project
做关于文本布局的应用
that has a lot of text layout and stuff in it,
就应该从这里入手
this is where you get started there.
我们来演示一下
Okay? So let’s have a demo
结合上节课讲过的
where we kind of combine all the things
关于 UITextView 的全部内容
we saw in last lecture in this UITextView.
我要叫这个演示 Attributor 属性
I’m going to call this demo “Attributor”
因为我们要用到属性化字符串
because we’re going to be doing attributed strings here.
它的样子呢
And it’s going to look like this.
这是一个新应用
It’s going to be a totally new app,
和 Matchismo 毫无关联
totally unrelated to Matchismo.
我要新建一个项目
So I’m going to say create new project.
隐藏其他面板
Let’s go ahead and also hide others here
已经设置好了
which we are doing.
我要选择单一视图应用
So I’m going to do a single view application.
我们总是选择这项 单一的 MVC
We almost always start with that, a single MVC.
我会在下节课中
This demo I’m eventually going to
将这个示例应用变成多 MVC 的应用
make into a multi-MVC application at the next lecture,
但是这里我们先选择单一视图
but we’re going to start here with this.
我要叫它 Attributor 属性
So I’m going to call it Attributor.
类前缀为 Attributor
I’m going to have the class prefix be attributor
这样我们的控制器就叫做 AttributorViewController
so that our controller is called AttributorViewController.
这样做就行了
Just do that.
我要把它保存在 Developer 目录下
I’m going to put it in Developer,
和 Matchismo 保存在同样的地方
same place I have Matchismo.
这是我的根目录 Developer
This is my home directory, Developer.
这里不需要源代码控制
I’m not going to use source control.
这就好了
And here we go.
这只是一个普通的应用 和我们以前做过的一样
So this is just a regular app just as you’re used to.
同样 我要将这些委托内容移到 Supporting Files 中
Again, I like to move these delegate things into supporting files
因为我们目前用不到委托
because we’re not really going to be doing the delegate.
这学期讲到 iOS7 多任务处理的时候
This quarter we might actually do the delegates
我们可能才会真正用到委托
when we start talking about multitasking in iOS 7.
大部分情况下
But for most of the time
你可以直接将它们移走
you can just kind of move that out of the way.
这是我的空白 storyboard
Here’s my blank storyboard.
这里我也要把它改为小尺寸的
Again, I’m going to go down to small size
这样更适合屏幕显示
instead of the tall size just so it fits.
这样做没什么特殊原因 只是更方便显示
Okay, there’s no reason to do that, except for that it fits.
大家在作业中也可以用大尺寸版本
By the way, you’re welcome to use the larger size in your homework if you want
因为我会要求大家在作业中实现越来越多的功能
because as I ask you to do more and more in the homework,
那样你就需要更大的空间 所以大点没问题
then you kind of need more and more space, which is fine.
当然 在设计用户界面时
Of course, we need to think a little bit
我们需要考虑到
when we design user interfaces
有些用户可能在小屏幕手机上运行应用
that this application might run on some users on smaller phones
而有些用户可能用的是大屏幕手机
and on some users on larger phones, right?
所以我们需要一个可以伸缩的用户界面
So we kind of need a user interface that can stretch.
下周我们会介绍自动布局机制
And next week we’ll be talking about autolayout,
iOS 的这种机制可以让你在设计用户界面时
which is a mechanism in iOS for you to design a user interface
指定它的拉伸和缩小的方式
and specify how it stretches and shrinks, okay,
非常重要
which is really important.
不只适用于不同大小的 iPhone
And not just on different size iPhones
还适用于不同的设备 比如 iPad
but different devices — iPads,
你可能会在 iPad 的一个小窗口中使用它们等等
you might be using them in a little window inside an iPad, etc.
我们希望 MVC 的视图是可伸缩的
We want to make our views of our MVCs be shrinkable
至少在某种程度上
to at least some extent.
当然也不要忘记设备的旋转问题
And of course, don’t forget device rotation.
当设备旋转后
When you turn your device,
它突然变成了宽比长高
it all of a sudden gets wider than it is tall.
所有元素都需要移动 以适应新的布局
Okay? Well, everything needs to move around to deal with that, too.
我们会在下周讲这部分内容
Okay? So we’ll talk about all of that next week.
我先让大家看看我要构建的用户界面
So let me show you the user interface I want to build here first
这样你们就会明白我想实现什么目标
so that you can kind of understand where I’m headed,
然后我们再编写代码实现它
and then we’ll write the code to do it.
它主要以一个 UITextView 为中心
It’s going to be primarily centered around a UITextView.
我可以在这里查看能拖拽出的各种对象
So here I am looking at all my various things that I can drag out.
拉到下面 找到 UITextView
So I’m going to go down here to UITextView,
应该在这 在哪呢
which is right — where is that thing?
太往下了
Too far down.
我找不到 UITextView 了
UITextView — I can’t find it.
在这呢
It’s right there.
UITextView 用来显示多行文本
Okay? So UITextView displays multiple lines of text.
我把它拖出来
So I drag it out.
默认情况下 它是充满全屏的
By default it wants to be the whole size of the screen.
但我其实要在这里加点按钮什么的
But I’m actually going to put some other buttons and stuff in here,
所以我要把它拉小一点
so I’m going to resize this to be smaller.
我还想让它有一点边
I also want it to have a little bit of edges here.
注意 我在 UI 中进行操作时
Now, notice that as I do everything in the UI,
借助了这些蓝色的线
I’m using these blue lines.
我还没真正告诉大家为什么要这么做
And I haven’t really told you exactly why that is,
但是当我们讲到
but when we start talking about
可变大小的视图
having these flexible-sized views
需要调整视图的大小时
that are going to want to resize,
这些蓝线有重要的作用
these blue lines play a crucial role.
所以当你们构建自己的 UI 时
And so when you’re building your UIs,
尽量使用蓝线
use the blue lines as much as possible
因为这样当我们处理自动布局时
because then when we start doing autolayout,
蓝线可以帮助自动布局系统
the blue lines are going to help the autolayout system
明白它们需要做怎样的处理
kind of get a clue as to what they should be doing.
好的
All right.
我要把这个文本视图放在这
So I’m going to have this text view here.
然后我想添加一些文本
And what I want to do is have some text.
我就直接用默认文本了
And I’ll just use the default text.
在创建文本视图时 如果你看这里
If you look over here when you create a text view,
可以看到这些伪拉丁文本
you see you get this kind of pseudo-Latin text here.
我就直接用这段默认文本了
Then I’ll just use that as the default.
所以这就是这个应用运行时
So that’s going to be the text
会显示出的文本
that’s going to be in this when I run.
运行应用时 就会得到这段文本
And if I run this, I’ll just get this text.
但是我还想要选择某些文本
But what I want to be able to do is select some of the text.
所以我要把这段文本设置为可选择的
So I’m going to make this text selectable, okay –
但是不能编辑 只能选择
not editable, though; just selectable.
这样我就能选择这里的某些单词了
And so I can select words in here.
我还想改变单词的颜色
And I want to be able to change the color of the words,
也许在字符外加个轮廓
maybe put a little outline around the characters, okay?
在这里做一些能用属性化字符串实现的功能
Do some fun stuff that we can do with attributed string in here.
我会允许应用做什么呢
And what am I going to allow us to do?
我们看看
Well, let’s see.
我们在下面添加几个按钮
Let me go get some buttons down here at the bottom.
我们加一个添加轮廓功能怎么样
How about let’s allow outlining.
在下面这里添加一个按钮 叫做 Outline
So I’m going to create a button down here called “Outline.”
当然了 也可以去除轮廓
And of course, let’s also let us unoutline.
那我就在这里再添加一个按钮
So I’ll create another button up here.
叫它 Unoutline
I’ll call it “Unoutline.”
这也许不是个单词 但是可以理解它的功能
That’s probably not a word, but we know what we want.
我同样还要借助蓝线
Again, I’m going to use the blue lines to try and get things,
让它们尽量对齐
you know, lined up as much as possible.
我们把这个按钮放在这个角
This guy, let’s put him right in the corner.
让这些按钮基准线对齐
These guys will line the base lines up.
这就是这两条线的含义
That’s what the double line right there means,
代表其他按钮所对齐的基准线
that the baseline of the other button line up.
同样 右边线也对齐了
And we got, also, this right line was lined up.
这样它们就会紧跟边缘变化 保持对齐
So they’re going to stick to the edges and stay lined up.
我们允许添加和去除轮廓
So we’ll allow outlining and unoutlining.
我还要允许设置颜色
And then also, I’m going to allow setting colors.
我要用的方法很有意思
And the way I’m going to do that is kind of fun.
我们先拖出一个按钮
So let’s get a button out here.
正好可以讲一下如何改变大小
This is a good way to talk about if I’m resizing,
我想让这个按钮大小为 6464
I want this button to be 64 by 64.
我知道这个尺寸很合适
I know that that’s a good size.
我可以一点点调整 将它设置为我想要的准确大小
And I could try and get it exactly the size I want.
但是如果你知道目标尺寸 这样做更简单
But it’s actually much easier — if you know the size you want –
也就是打开这里的尺寸检查器
to go over here in the size inspector.
看到这个尺寸检查器了吗
You see this size inspector?
你可以在这里直接输入 我想要 6464 的
And you can just type in, “I want 64 by 64,” okay?
关于尺寸检查器的内容
So this size inspector, we’re going to see
我们会在讲自动布局时详细讲解
when we start talking about autolayout a lot
下面会有很多内容
there’s going to be a lot of stuff down here,
代表元素在改变尺寸后
describing how this thing gets constrained
具有怎样的约束
when things change size.
这里同样可以设置尺寸
But it’s also good for setting the size.
尺寸设置好以后
And then once the size is set,
我把它放在一个合适的地方 像这样
I’ll move into a nice spot like that.
现在我可以加一个单词 Red 红色
Now, I could put, like, the word “Red” here
将 Red 显示在按钮上
and make this a button that has the word “Red” on it.
我可以让文本变为红色
And I could make the text be red.
这就是我希望这个按钮实现的功能
That’s what I want this button to do.
当我点击按钮后 我希望选中的文本变为红色
When I click here, I want whatever’s selected to turn red.
但我不想用单词表示 我想直接使用颜色
But instead of using words, I’m actually going to use the color.
我只要转到检查器
I’m just going to go to the inspector.
因为按钮继承自控制 而控制继承自视图
And since a button inherits from control and control inherits from view,
明白继承层次在检查器中是怎样的了吧
see how that inheritance hierarchy is working in the inspector,
我要到下面这里改变它的背景颜色
I’m going to go down here and change its background color,
这和我们之前
which is the same thing we did
设置整个视图的背景为绿色的操作是一样的
when we set the background of the whole view to green.
我要将它设置为 比如说红色
And I’m going to set this one to — let’s say this one’s red.
现在我就有了一个好看的红色按钮
Okay? So now I have a nice red button here.
当我点击这个按钮
And when I click on this,
我要将它连起来 让文本变为红色
I’m going to have to wire it up to make this turn red.
我们再添加一些其他颜色的按钮
So let’s make some more buttons here of different colors.
同样 借助蓝线
Again, I’m using the blue lines.
看到它们沿线对齐了吗
See how they’re snapping in place?
借助蓝线
Okay. Getting blue lines –
当然要尽可能多地使用蓝线
definitely want blue lines as much as possible.
这里我们把它的背景设为绿色
So here let’s make this background be green.
把它设为橙色
I’ll make this one be orange,
把它设为紫色
make this one be — oh, I don’t know — purple.
好了 现在我们有了设置颜色和轮廓按钮
Okay? So now we have some colors and some outlines.
然后我们把它…
And then let’s also make this thing –
我们在上面这里再加一个标题吧
well, let’s put a headline at the top here, too.
再拖出一个按钮
So let me grab another button –
实际上 这里用标签就可以了
actually, let’s do a label for this one
因为它不需要点击功能
because we’re not going to make it clickable.
所以我要在上面这里添加一个标签
So I’m going to put a label here at the top.
加上比如说 CS193p Rocks
I’m going to put something like “CS193p Rocks.”
这就是它的标题
Okay. So that’s just going to be my title of this thing.
我希望它居中 看起来好看一点
I want it nice and centered.
把它移到上面
Let’s move this up so that it’s locked.
调整至最大尺寸
Let’s resize it so it’s maximum space. It locks.
现在我就完成了这个好看的用户界面
And so now I’ve got this nice user interface.
所有元素都借助了蓝线
I’ve used blue guidelines for everything;
它们都贴着某条蓝线
everyone’s sticking on a blue guideline.
这样处理 非常有利于
That’s going to be really advantageous for us
实现它的自动布局功能
when we try to do autolayout with it.
现在 我们讲讲
Now, let’s talk a little bit
我想在这里用的字体
about the fonts I want to use here.
我在幻灯片中讲过了
And I told you in the slides
在显示用户内容时
that when you’re displaying user content, okay,
最好使用系统推荐字体
you want to use the preferred fonts of the system.
我就要这样做 对它
Okay? And that’s what I’m going to do, both for this guy.
它显然是用户内容
This is clearly the user content.
这两个按钮不是用户内容
These two buttons are not user content.
它们继续使用系统字体
They’re going to stay the system fonts, okay,
因为它们是按钮
because they’re buttons.
但是这个标题和正文是用户内容
But this title and this body are kind of user contents.
你可以质疑这个标题算不上是用户内容
You could argue that the title is not quite user content,
但它确实算是
but it kind of is.
它可能通过本地化变为另外一种语言
It might get localized to another language
或者根据应用内容的不同变为其他文本
or it might change, depending on what’s going on.
我也不知道
I don’t know.
但它确实属于标题
But it’s really kind of a headline.
所以我要用标题字体
So I’m going to use the headline font
来显示这里的标签
to display this guy right here –
实际上 我还想让它居中
actually, I also want this centered.
好吧
All right.
确认一下它是居中的
So let’s make sure that’s centered.
选择标题字体
And so the way you pick the headline font,
标题样式推荐字体的方法是
the preferred font which is headline,
检查标签 然后选择这里的字体
is you inspect the label and you go here to the fonts.
可以看到目前设置为系统字体
And you can see that it’s currently set to be a system font.
我要向下找到文本样式 选择标题
And I’m going to go down here to text styles and pick headline.
这如果用代码来实现
And that’s basically in the code
基本就是 preferredFontForTextStyle: Headline
like saying preferred font for text style headline.
可以看到这里变了
And you can see it change there.
加粗了一点
Kind of got a little bold to it.
现在它是标题字体了
It’s now the headline font.
文本视图也是一样
And the same thing here, the text view,
我也要将它设置为推荐字体
I’m also going to set it to use a preferred font.
但是这里我要选择正文字体
But in this case I’m going to use the body font
因为很明显
because this is clearly, like,
它是这个窗口中内容的正文
the body of this content in this window.
现在我已经将它们设置为了推荐字体
So now I’ve set these things to have the preferred fonts
不再是系统字体了
rather than the system fonts.
这基本上就是需要设置的全部内容了
And that’s pretty much all that’s required to set that up.
这就是我的 UI
So that’s my UI.
明白吗
All right?
有问题吗
So yeah, question?
iOS 中是否有制作圆角按钮的简便方法
In iOS is there an easy way to round out the corners of those buttons,
还是说必须做很多蒙版
or do you have to go through, like, a lot of masking?
问题是 如果我想将这些按钮
Yeah, so the question is: If I wanted these to be, like,
变为圆角矩形
rounded rect buttons –
在 iOS7 中
which it’s not really a thing in iOS 7
圆角矩形按钮很容易实现
to have rounded rect buttons, by the way;
在 iOS6 中是个问题 但在 iOS7 中就不是很麻烦了
it was a thing in iOS 6, but not so much a thing in iOS 7 –
实现圆角矩形有多难呢
how difficult would this be?
答案是不会那么麻烦
And the answer is it wouldn’t be that bad.
并不是很难
It wouldn’t be that hard.
有一个机制
There’s a mechanism.
圆角矩形用一行代码就可以实现
Rounded rect is a one-liner to create a rounded rect.
我们也许并不会改变这些 UI 按钮
And probably we wouldn’t make these UI buttons;
只是改变它们的视图
we’d just make them views.
只用一行代码就可以编写一个点击手势
And it’s really a one-liner to have a tap gesture,
点击它 让它执行某些操作
to tap on it and cause it to do something.
所以只用几行代码 并不是很难
So, you know, a few lines of code is really not that difficult.
实际上 不只是圆角矩形
In fact, you can make it not just rounded rect
你可以将它变为任意形状
but any shape that you wanted there, whatever.
有问题吗
Question?
有没有什么方法能够添加 CSS 文件呢
Is there any way to include, like, CSS in it though or no?
问题是 有没有什么方法能加入 CSS 文件
So the question is: Is there any way to include CSS?
没有什么直接的方法
Not really directly.
但是 比如说这些推荐字体
However, these preferred fonts, for example,
就用到了 CSS 系统
are plugged into the CSS system.
如果你的应用中某些内容来源于 CSS
So if you have content in your app that is coming from CSS source,
比如网页视图之类的
you know, on a web view or something –
我们还没讲过这部分内容
we haven’t talked about any of that yet,
但是你可以这样做
but you could do that –
字体会进行匹配 彼此同步
the fonts can match up and all synchronize with each other.
所以有一些同步性的处理
So there’s some synchronicity there,
但是你不能直接显示
but you can’t directly display.
好的 接下来我们看看代码
Okay. So let’s look at the code
让这个用户界面实现我们想要的功能
to make this user interface do what we want.
打开系统编辑器
So I’m going to get my system editor up here.
把这部分移到最左边
Let’s put that right on the edge.
腾出更大地方 方便显示更多代码
Let’s make some more space so you can see more code.
可以看到 默认的视图控制器中有一个这样的方法
And you can see that my default view controller has this method here,
viewDidLoad 它是视图控制器生命周期的一部分
viewDidLoad, which is part of the view controller lifecycle
我们等下就会讲到这部分
that we’re going to talk about in a second
还有这个 didReceiveMemoryWarning 方法
and also didReceiveMemoryWarning,
严格来说 它并不属于视图控制器生命周期
which is not strictly speaking part of the view controller lifecycle
但是我还是会把它
but I’m going to talk about it
放在视图控制器生命周期中讲
as part of the view controller lifecycle.
今天我不会对它进行演示
I’m not going to demo that today,
但是稍后我会演示 viewDidLoad 的用法
but I am later going to demo viewDidLoad.
所以我们把它留下
So we’ll leave that in there for now.
现在它什么都做不了 只有 super 调用和一条注释
Right now it doesn’t do anything except for call super and have a comment.
对吧
Okay?
那么我需要在这里做什么呢
So what do I need to do here?
两件事情
Couple of things.
一是我想要设置
One, I’m going to want to be setting
它的可变字符串属性
the mutable string attributes of this thing,
所以我需要一个连接到它的输出口
so I need an outlet to this.
我只要按住 control 键拖动到这里 创建一个输出口
So I’m just going to control drag here to create an outlet.
我要叫它 body
I’m going to call it “body,” okay,
因为它就像是我的正文
because it’s kind of like my body.
可以看到它是一个 UITextView
Text view, you can see that it’s a UITextView.
我可以向 body 发送消息
And I’m going to be able to send a message to this body
得到它保存文本的可变字符串
to get its text storage mutable string.
然后我可以设置属性了
And then I’m just going to start setting attributes.
对吧 就是这么简单
Okay? It’s as simple as that.
我还要再向这里添加一个输出口
You know, I’m also going to grab one to this,
等下你们就会知道原因
and you’ll see why later.
我要叫它 headline
I’m going to call this my “headline,” Okay?
我也可以叫它 header 或者 heading
And so I could call that my “header,” or my “heading,”
或者 title label 之类的
or “title label,” or something like that.
这里我就要叫它 headline 了
I’m going to call it “headline” just here
用来强调我们讨论的是推荐字体
to emphasize that we’re talking about preferred fonts
我也会在示例中演示这一部分
because I’m going to be showing that in the demo as well.
我们设置好了 body 和 headline 两个输出口
So we’ve got this body and the headline.
我们可以设置标题
We could conceivably set things about the headline.
我没有时间具体操作了
I don’t really have time for that,
但是我们会对这里的正文进行设置
but we will be setting things in here.
这里有这些用于改变颜色的按钮
We’ve got these colored buttons.
我们先实现这部分
Let’s do those first.
所以我要按住 control 键进行拖拽
So I’m going to control drag here
这样当我们按下按钮时 会发送操作
to have an action sent when we press on that button.
我要叫这个操作为
I’m going to call this action
changeBodySelectionColorToMatchBackgroundOfButton 将所选正文颜色变为按钮背景颜色
”changeBodySelectionColorToMatchBackgroundOfButton.”
你们可能觉得很好笑 心里想着
Okay? Now, you might laugh and say,
这个方法的名字真长
”Whoa, that’s a long name method.”
但在 Objective-C 尤其是 iOS 中
But long name methods are kind of preferred
倾向于使用较长的方法名称
generally in Objective-C and especially in iOS
因为 Xcode 会帮助你补全名称
because Xcode’s going to help you escape complete these things.
如果你可以为方法起一个这样的名称
And if you can have a method name like this
准确表达出方法的作用
that really matches and says exactly what it does,
是一件很好的事情
that can be a good thing.
这属于编程的艺术
It’s an art of programming thing.
我要将参数变为 UIButton
I’m going to change the argument to be a UIButton,
和我们之前在 Connect 中所做操作一样
just like we did before in Connect.
这个方法是做什么的
So what does this method do?
希望通过这个长名字
Well, hopefully with that long name
可以清楚地说明它的作用
it’s clear what that does, right?
不管选中了这里正文的哪些内容
It changes whatever the selection is in our body right here,
这个方法都会将选中文本的颜色
it changes the color of that
设置为这个按钮的视图背景颜色
to match the background view of this button.
这就是这个方法的功能
Okay? That’s what this method is going to do.
这个方法只需要一行代码
This method is one line of code.
我们来看看这行代码
Okay? So let’s look at that one line of code.
我们需要设置正文中可变字符串的属性
We need to set attributes of the mutable string of our body.
所以这里我要写 self.body.textStorage
So I’m going to say self.body.textStorage.
我得到了 NSMutableAttributedString
Now I have the NSMutableAttributedString –
textStorage 是它的一个子类
textStorage is a subclass of it –
但它是一个 NSMutableString
but it is an NSMutableString.
我只想增加一个属性
And I just want to add an attribute,
代表选中文本的前景颜色
which is the foreground color of whatever’s selected there.
这个属性叫做
So the attribute is called
NSForegroundColorAttributeName
”NSForegroundColorAttributeName.”
它的值就是我们想要设置的颜色
Okay? The value — that’s the color we want to set it to –
我说了 我们想让它
well, I said we’re going to have it
与按钮的背景颜色相同
match the background of the button.
所以我要用 sender
So I’m going to say sender,
也就是发送它的按钮
which is the button that’s sending this thing,
然后是 backgroundColor 明白吗
backgroundColor, okay?
范围指的是文本视图保存内容的哪部分
And then the range is what range of this text view’s storage
是我想要设置为目标颜色的
do I want to set to be that color?
我说了我想改变的是正文的选中部分
Well, I said I want it to be the selection, the body selection –
文本视图中有一个方法叫做 selectedRange
so there’s a method in text view called “selectedRange.”
能够返回选中内容的 NSRange
And it returns an NSRange of what’s selected, okay,
用户选中的内容
what the user selection is.
就是这样一行代码
Okay? So you can see one line of code,
我们需要所有四种颜色都正常运行
and we’ve got our color — all four color buttons working
只要它们都正确连接好
as long as they’re all wired up,
现在它没问题了
which we know that this one is, right?
因为我们把它连上了
Okay, because we wired that one up.
这里显示连好了
There it is right there.
我们还没有连接这个按钮 我们来做一下
We haven’t wired this one up, but let’s do that.
还有这个
And this one.
以及这个
我们运行一下试试
Okay? So let’s go ahead and run.
我们试试看能不能在这个设备上运行
We’ll try and see if we can run it on the device over here
如果今天没问题的话
if that works today.
希望不会出现技术问题
Hopefully no technical issues will arise.
我们运行的是一个 iPhone 应用
Now, this is an iPhone app that we’re running here,
而我们要在 iPad 上运行
and we’re running it on an iPad.
我的演示设备恰好是一台 iPad
My demo machine happens to be an iPad.
所以程序运行在 iPhone 模拟模式下
So this is running kind of in iPhone emulation mode, okay,
iOS7 的 iPhone 模拟模式
which is actually better in iOS 7
比之前 iOS 版本中的更好
than it was in previous versions of iOS.
并不完全相同
It’s not quite exactly the same.
注意顶部的这个状态栏
You notice that this status bar at the top,
并没有运营商
you don’t get the, you know, what your carrier is,
电池寿命等信息
and the battery life, and all that stuff.
这些内容被去掉了
That’s kind of cut off.
但是除此之外还是非常相似的
But otherwise it’s pretty similar.
可以看到这段伪拉丁文本显示在了这里
So you can see that we got that kind of pseudo-Latin text in there,
它是可以滚动的
and it’s scrollable.
也可以选中
And it’s also selectable.
我只要在单词上双击
So I just double tapped on that word.
就选中了它
And we got it now.
这些内容是系统自动实现的 比如定义单词
You get things for free on this, like defining words –
在词典中进行查找
looking them up in the dictionary.
如果点击这里的定义 会转到词典进行查找
So if we hit define right here, it goes and looks it up –
没有找到 不奇怪
not found, not understand, no surprise there.
但是可以查单词
But you can look that up.
当然了 希望所有按钮都运行正常
And of course, hopefully all our buttons work.
我们试试红色
So let’s try red.
起作用了
That worked.
还有橙色和紫色
And orange and purple.
没问题 绿色呢
Okay? Green.
也运行正常
So that’s working.
设置都没问题
That’s setting things right.
我还可以扩大选中范围 点击橙色按钮
I could actually extend my selection, go orange.
将它们全部设置为橙色
Sets it all orange.
选择另一个单词 设为红色
Pick another word, red.
没问题
So that’s working.
非常简单
Super easy.
以上内容 大家都明白吗
Okay? Everyone understand what we’ve done so far?
我们继续
So now let’s go on
实现添加和去除轮廓按钮的功能
and do the outline button and the unoutline button.
所以我只要从这里按住 control 键进行拖拽
So I’m just going to control drag from there.
我要叫它 outline
I’m going to call this “outline.”
这里不需要任何参数
I don’t need any argument here
因为我们不需要根据按钮来决定操作
because I’m not looking at the button to determine how to do it.
实际上 为了不使用长消息名称
And in fact, in spirit of not long message names,
我们叫它 outlineBodySelection
let’s call it “outlineBodySelection.”
这样可以更清楚地表现出
Okay, because that’s kind of even clearer exactly
要给什么元素加轮廓
what the outline is going to outline.
我们实现一下
So let’s do that.
我们创建好了 outlineBodySelection
Here we have outlineBodySelection.
这个也和刚才一样 body.textStorage
Again, this one’s same thing as before — body.textStorage –
我们要添加属性
and we’re going to add attribute.
实际上 想要添加轮廓 我们需要做两件事
But actually, to do an outline we need to do two things.
一是我们需要设置描边宽度
One thing is we need to set the stroke width, okay?
也就是字符被描边的宽度
That’s the width that the character gets stroked –
不是填充 而是描边 它的外边缘
not filled but stroked, its outer edge.
我们还想设置描边的颜色
And we also want to set the color of that stroke.
我想设成黑色
I want it to be black.
所以如果我们有一个单词 颜色已选定
Okay? So if we have a word and its color is selected,
这个单词还是会填充选定的颜色
it will still fill with that color, okay,
我要指定描边 进行填充和描边
because I’m going to specify a stroke that does a fill and a stroke.
但是轮廓会是黑色
But the outline’s going to be in black.
所以当我们添加属性时 需要使用 addAttributes
So when we do add attribute, we need to do add attributes –plural
添加两个属性
because we’re going to add two attributes.
这是一个词典
Now, this is a dictionary,
我可以在这里用 @和大括号
and I can just create this dictionary right on the fly here
创建词典
with our at sign curly brace.
我们需要一个描边宽度属性
And one of the things we want is the stroke width.
这是 StrokeWidthAttributeName
So here’s the StrokeWidthAttributeName.
我要将它设置为 -3
And I’m going to set the stroke width to minus three.
如果你还记得的话
Okay? Minus three, if you’ll recall,
-3 表示描边宽度为 3 并进行填充
means stroke width of three and also fill.
如果将其设置为 3 就不会进行填充
If I said stroke width of at sign three, it would not fill.
描边会是空心的
It would be clear.
对吧 中间是没有颜色的
Right? In the middle of it would be clear.
我们不想要这种效果
So we don’t want that.
我们希望描边是实心的
We want to fill.
无论我们选择了哪种颜色
Whichever color we pick, we want that to.
就是这样
So that’s that.
然后我们还要将描边颜色属性
And then let’s also set the stroke color attribute
设置为 UIColor blackColor
to be UIColor blackColor.
我做这个操作主要是为了让大家明白
So I’m just doing this mostly so you can see how to put,
如何在代码里直接使用颜色
you know, an actual color in there
而这个颜色是我们从别处抓取的
instead of here where we grabbed a color from somewhere else.
你可以用这些 UIColor 中的类方法来实现
You can use these class methods in UIColor to do that.
我们需要范围
And we need the range.
和之前一样 selectedRange
Same thing as before: selectedRange.
所以现在我添加了这两个属性
Okay? So now we’re gonna
以实现添加轮廓功能
add both those attributes to outline it.
这就是我们需要的全部内容
That’s all we need there.
顺便在这里继续实现去除轮廓的功能
Let’s do unoutline while we’re here.
节省一点时间
Save ourselves a little bit of time.
我要叫它 unoutlineBodySelection
I’m going to call this “unoutlineBodySelection.”
好了 为了向大家示范一个不同的方法
Done. And just again to show you a different method,
我们通过移除描边宽度属性来实现去除轮廓
let’s unoutline by removing any stroke width attribute.
也可以将描边宽度设为 0
I could probably set the stroke width to zero as well.
但这里我要用移除属性的方法 这样大家就能明白
But I’m going to remove so that you can see
如何在 NSMutableAttributedString 中移除属性了
how in NSMutableAttributedString we can remove attributes.
我们只要写
We just say
removeAttribute: NSStrokeWidthAttributeName range: self.body.selectedRange
removeAttribute: NSStrokeWidthAttributeName range: self.body.selectedRange.
这样就可以移除那个属性
Okay? So that’s going to remove that attribute.
我们并不需要移除描边颜色
We don’t really need to remove the stroke color
因为如果根本就没有描边
because if it’s not being stroked,
颜色也就无从谈起
then the color doesn’t matter.
所以可以把它留下
So it’s kind of in there.
有点多余
It’s a little extra.
你可能认为这样会浪费存储空间
You could argue maybe wasted storage.
属性化字符串的存储
Although the storage of attributed string
得到了极好的优化
is really optimized to the nth degree.
所以我不会过多担心
Okay? So I wouldn’t worry too terribly much about that.
好吧
All right.
我们看看是否能正常运行
So let’s go see if that works.
再选择一个单词 比如它 添加轮廓
Okay. So let’s pick another word here like this one, outline it.
添加上了
That is outlined.
看起来只是加粗了 因为它本身填充颜色就是黑色的
It just looks bold because it’s filled with black still.
本来就是黑色的
Okay? Because black was the color that’s there.
但是如果我用橙色填充它
But if I fill it with orange,
现在看起来就不太一样了
you can see it looks a little different.
对吧 或者选这个单词
Right? Or go over here to this word.
变为红色 然后添加轮廓 明白吗
Let’s make it red and then outline it, okay?
大家都明白了吗
Everyone cool with that?
我们也可以去除轮廓
Then we can unoutline as well.
再变为红色
Go back to red.
这就是添加和去除轮廓
So outline, unoutline.
大家明白了吗
Okay? Everyone understand that?
现在就先这样了
Okay. So that’s it for now.
我们等会再回来
We’ll be back to this in a second.
请讲
Yeah?
我不是很清楚
Yeah, I’m not quite sure that I understand the difference
-3 和 +3 的区别
between the negative three and positive three.
什么样子是被填充了 什么样子不是呢
Like, what’s getting filled or isn’t getting filled?
好问题
Okay. Great question.
确认一下
So let’s just be a hundred percent clear:
我们这里用的 -3
What’s the difference between the negative three
和 +3 有什么区别
that we have right here, okay, and positive three?
-3 表示… 这样吧
Negative three means — in fact, you know what?
稍后我会在演示里做一下
I’ll show you a demo of it a little later.
看见这个 Outline 按钮了吗
See the button that says “Outline”?
等会我们会为它添加轮廓
Later we’re going to change it to be Outlined.
我们不会填充它 这样大家就能看到
Okay? And we won’t fill it, and you’ll see the difference,
不用颜色填充的不同之处了
that it’s not going to be filled with a color, okay?
我们回到幻灯片
So let’s get back to the slides, though.
回到这里
And over here.
看下一张幻灯片
Next. Okay?
视图控制器生命周期
View controller lifecycle.
理解它很重要
Okay. So this is important thing to understand,
视图控制器生命周期
the view controller lifecycle,
因为你需要控制的很多
because a lot of the things that you’re going to control
关于视图控制器如何随时间变化的操作
about how your view controller moves through time
都要用到视图控制器生命周期中的方法
are going to be controlled by the methods
来实现控制
that are part of the view controller lifecycle.
视图控制器生命周期
Now, all the view controller lifecycle is,
就是一系列的方法
is a series of methods, okay,
当事件发生时 会被发送至 UIViewController
that are sent to UIViewController when things happen.
你的控制器是 UIViewController 的一个子类
Now, your controller is a subclass of UIViewController.
你可能已经注意到了
You probably noticed that.
如果你看看代码
If you look at your code,
会发现你新建应用时
you’ll see that your controller that gets created for you
由模板创建的控制器
by the template when you create a new app
是 UIViewController 的一个子类
is a subclass of UIViewController.
它会发送这些消息
So it’s going to be sent these messages,
如果你想要知道这些事件何时发生
and you’re going to override them
就要重写这些方法
if you want to find out when these things are happening.
不要忘了调用超类
Don’t forget to call super. Okay?
你为什么需要这些东西
Why do you need these things?
你需要对控制器进行初始化
Well, you need to be able to initialize your controller;
你需要知道自己何时在屏幕上出现和消失
you need to be able to find when you come on and off screen;
你需要知道边界何时改变
you need to know when your bounds change, right,
你的几何变化
your geometry changes.
你需要知道这些消息
You got to know these things
这样你的视图控制器的视图
for your view controller’s view
才能在 iOS 环境中正常运行
to successfully live in the iOS world.
这个生命周期开始于创建 对吗
So the start of this lifecycle is creation, okay?
大部分视图控制器都是从 storyboard 中创建的
Most view controllers are created out of storyboards.
我讲过了 storyboard 不会生成代码
And I told you that storyboards don’t generate code.
你基本上是直接编辑这些对象
You’re basically editing those objects live –
那个 UITextView 那些按钮
that UITextView, those buttons –
你直接在 Xcode 中编辑它们
you’re editing them live in Xcode.
然后当保存 storyboard 时
And when that storyboard gets saved,
它们像是被冷冻干燥了
they kind of get freeze-dried.
然后当你运行应用时
And then when your application runs,
水又回来了 它们又活过来了
water gets added back to them and they come back to life, okay?
这是生命周期的创建部分
So that’s the creation part of the lifecycle.
在创建时 我们并不做很多事情
And we don’t really do much at creation.
实际上 我要把创建这部分的内容
In fact, I’m not even going to talk about creation
放在视图控制器生命周期的最后讲
until the very end of the view controller lifecycle.
尽管按发生顺序来说 它是开始
Even though it is chronologically the beginning,
但却是目前最不重要的
it’s by far the least important.
所以我把它放在最后
So I’m emphasizing that by putting it at the end.
创建之后 你会经历以下过程
But after it’s created, you go through the following process.
设置好输出口 对吧
Your outlets get set, okay?
这些输出口必须设置好
Got to have those outlets set.
然后你的视图控制器出现在屏幕上
Then your view controller appears on screen
它也许会从屏幕上消失
and it might disappear from screen.
你还没有见过它消失
You haven’t seen that yet
因为目前
because right now
你的整个应用中就只有一个视图控制器
you’ve only had one view controller in your whole app.
只有应用退出时 它才会消失
It only disappears when the app quits.
但是如果你有多个视图控制器
But when you have multiple view controllers,
它们会交替在屏幕上出现和消失
they’ll appear and disappear on screen.
它们的几何变化
Their geometry changes –
无论是因为旋转
either device rotation
还是其他原因造成的
or something else can cause their bounds to change
MVC 的视图的边界变化
of your view of your MVC.
内存不足的情况
Low memory situations –
严格来说并不属于视图控制器生命周期
again, not strictly speaking part of the view controller lifecycle
但这也可能在运行时出现
but that can happen while you’re running.
每一步都会调用一个方法
And at each of these steps a method gets called.
我们先看第一个方法 ViewDidLoad
So let’s look at the first one: ViewDidLoad.
我们在代码中见过它 我没有删掉它
So that’s the one we saw in the code that I didn’t delete.
这里很适合于
This is a really great place
放置控制器初始化代码
to put initialization code for your controller.
你可以把它看做是
You can kind of think of it
放置 init 全部内容的地方
as where you would put all the stuff from your init, okay,
因为你的 init 并不会被调用
because your init is not going to get called –
不会在视图控制器中调用 等下会看到
as you’re going to see — for your view controller.
它为什么比 init 更好呢
So why is this better than init?
因为你已经设置好了输出口
Because your outlets are set.
通常情况下 如果你想要初始化视图
Okay? Very important for your outlets to be set usually
设置好输出口是十分重要的
if you want to initialize your view.
因为你想让你的标签
Because you want to set your labels
显示些什么
to say something or whatever.
在 Matchismo 中 开始时是牌面向下的
You know, in the Matchismo game we started with the cards facedown
因为我们当时不知道如何在开始时让牌面向上
because we didn’t really know how to start faceup.
这里就可以设置第一张牌
Okay? Well, this is where you would set the first card.
明白吗
All right?
你可以绘制第一张牌 让它…
You’d draw the first card, have it –
说的是 Matchismo 不是你们的作业 是我们在课上做的
this is the Matchismo, not your assignment but what we did in class –
想让卡牌在开始时牌面向上
have it start with the card faceup.
你要在 viewDidLoad 中实现
You would do this in viewDidLoad
因为这里输出口都设置好了
because here your outlets are set.
我可以向按钮发送消息
So I can talk to that button.
当时 Matchismo 只有一个按钮
It was a single button in Matchismo at the time.
但是我还没有出现在屏幕上
But I’m not on screen yet.
你在屏幕上出现之前 viewDidLoad 会被调用
ViewDidLoad gets called before you come on screen.
所以这里很适合执行这类操作
So it’s a great place to do stuff like that.
在控制器生命周期中
ViewDidLoad will only ever be called once
viewDidLoad 只会被调用一次
in the lifetime of your controller.
一个周期中只会被调用一次
Period. Once.
绝不会多于一次
It never gets called more than once.
这是一个绝好的地方
Okay? It is a spectacularly great place
来放置初始化代码
to put initialization code.
但是有一些操作是不可以在 viewDidLoad 中可执行的
However, there are limits to what can go in viewDidLoad,
尤其是关于几何的代码
most especially geometry code.
viewDidLoad 被调用时
At the time viewDidLoad is called,
视图的边界还没有定下来
the bounds of your view is not finalized.
它也许只是待在 storyboard 里
It’s probably just sitting at whatever it was in the storyboard,
当它出现在屏幕上时 也许不会出现在预定位置
which may or may not be what’s going to happen when it’s on screen
因为它运行在一个不同的设备上
because it might be on a little different device,
在不同的地点 或者被旋转了之类的
or different place, or it might be rotated, or something like that.
所以不要在 viewDidLoad 中添加与几何相关的代码
So you do not want to put geometry-related code –
换句话说 不要在 viewDidLoad 中
in other words, any initialization that has to do
添加任何关于视图形状的初始化信息
with what the shape of your view is — in viewDidLoad.
明白吗
Okay?
这是 viewDidLoad 中的主要限制
That’s the major restriction in viewDidLoad.
但除此之外 这是执行初始化的好地方
But otherwise, it’s a great place
因为它在输出口设置好 你出现在屏幕上之前
because it only gets called once before you go on screen
只会被调用一次
after your outlets get set.
这是一个很棒的方法
It’s an awesome method.
强烈推荐
Okay? Highly recommend it.
在你的视图控制器的视图就要出现在屏幕上之前
Now, just before your view controller view appears on screen,
系统会调用 viewWillAppear 方法
you get viewWillAppear.
这是一个放置代码的好地方
Okay? This is a pretty good place to put things.
在某些方面 它不如 viewDidLoad
It’s not really as awesome as viewDidLoad in some ways.
我甚至不确定是否在这里添加了几何相关内容
And I’m not even sure I’d put geometry-related stuff in here,
下面的幻灯片中可以看到
as you’ll see in a couple of slides.
但是 确实有一些内容要放在这里
However, there are some things you do want to put in here.
需要注意的一点是
Now, one thing you want to be careful about
不要在 viewWillAppear 中添加一次性初始化内容
not putting in viewWillAppear is one-time initialization
这属于 viewDidLoad 的内容
that really belongs in ViewDidLoad
因为当应用中有多个 MVC 时
because, again, when you have multiple MVCs in your app,
它们会交替出现消失
they’re going to be appearing and disappearing.
所以 viewWillAppear
And so viewWillAppear is going to
会被多次调用
get called multiple times, okay?
每次视图重新在屏幕上显示时
Every time your view appears back on screen,
viewWillAppear 都会被再次调用
viewWillAppear gets called again.
所以如果你把一次性初始化操作
So if it’s a one-time initialization,
放在了 viewWillAppear 中
you put it in viewWillAppear,
每次视图重新出现时 都会被执行
it’s going to happen every time your thing reappears.
那么 viewWillAppear 中应该放些什么呢
So what does go in viewWillAppear?
如果你需要执行的某些初始化
Well, one thing is if there’s some initialization you need to do,
基于某些数据 而这些数据
based on some data that might have changed
可能会在视图控制器的视图离开屏幕时发生变化
while your view controller’s view was off screen.
懂吗 比如说你的模型
Okay? So like your model.
模型中的某些内容变了
Something changed in your model.
你的视图控制器不在屏幕上了
Your view controller was off screen,
它并没有监听模型的变化
so it wasn’t really listening for changes in the model.
然后它又回到了屏幕上
And then coming back on screen,
这时你最好与模型进行同步
you better sync up with the model.
这么说明白吗
Does that make sense?
你之前不在屏幕上了 现在又重新出现在屏幕上
Because you were off screen and now you’re appearing.
viewWillAppear 方法适合于
And so this is a good thing to put in viewWillAppear:
对不可见时可能改变的内容
Synchronization with things that might have changed
进行同步
while you weren’t visible,
包括
including things that, you know,
准备第一次出现前发生的变化
were changing before you appeared for the first time.
因为 viewWillAppear
Because viewWillAppear, of course,
也会在第一次出现时被调用
gets called the first time you appear as well.
这个方法不叫视图将要再次出现 叫视图将要出现
Okay? This is not view will reappear; it’s viewWillAppear.
所以放在这里很合适
Okay. So that’s a good thing to put in here.
我们会在后面的课程中讲到
We’ll talk later in the course
在这里添加代码以实现优化
about putting code in here for optimization purposes
因为如果你添加的操作需要大量资源
because if you put something that’s going to take lot of resources,
比如要在 viewDidLoad 中进行网络调用
like you’re going to make some network call in viewDidLoad,
如果你的 MVC 始终没有出现在屏幕上呢
and what if your MVC never appears on screen?
那 viewDidLoad 中的网络调用就浪费了时间
Well, you wasted that time doing that network call on viewDidLoad.
而如果放在 viewWillAppear 中执行
Whereas if you do it in viewWillAppear,
尽管你也要对它进行设计
even though you’re going to have to design it –
因为如果你要在网络中执行什么操作
because if you do something in the network,
会延迟一些才能返回结果
it’s going to come later;
并不会立即得到 这也没问题
it’s not going to be instantaneously available, that’s okay,
我们会讲到如何利用多线程解决这个问题
we’ll talk about how to do multithreaded, make that all work –
在 viewWillAppear 中开始
kicking it off in viewWillAppear
效果可能更好一些
might be a little better performance
因为当你收到 viewWillAppear 时
because you know when you get viewWillAppear
代表你的视图就要在屏幕上显示
that your view is going to appear on screen.
这时做些花销大的操作是值得的
Okay? So it’s worth it to do something expensive.
这是高级内容了
But that’s kind of advanced stuff.
目前不用太过担心这部分内容
So I won’t worry about that too much for now.
在这里视图的几何信息已经设置
The view’s geometry is set here.
所以可以在这里执行一些基于几何的初始化
So you could do some initialization based on geometry here.
很多人这样做 因为很简单
And a lot of people do it because it’s kind of simple.
但是还有一个地方
But there’s actually a better place
更适合于基于几何的初始化
to do geometry-based initialization.
但是没关系
But it’s okay.
可以在 viewWillAppear 中执行
It’s quote “Okay to do it in viewWillAppear”
只要你明白
as long as you understand
几何内容是可以在 viewWillAppear 之后改变的
that your geometry could change after viewWillAppear.
换句话说 你在屏幕上时
In other words, you can be on screen
有人旋转了手机
and someone could rotate the phone,
这样几何内容就被改变了
and now your geometry just changed.
你最好对这种情况进行处理
Okay? So you better deal with that, okay,
旋转时并不会得到 viewWillAppear
that you’re not going to get viewWillAppear when you rotate,
而是别的方法
you’re going to get other things.
当视图从屏幕上离开时 你也会得到通知
Okay. You also get notified when your view goes off screen.
也就是这个 viewWillDisappear
So that viewWillDisappear, okay?
要在这个方法里做些什么呢
And what do you want to do in here?
通常不会在这个方法中执行太多内容
You don’t usually do a lot of stuff in here.
如果你要做些动画之类的
If you’re doing something like animation or something,
显然可以在这里停止动画
obviously this would be a good place to stop doing that
因为出现 viewWillDisappear 时
because when viewWillDisappear happen,
你希望你的控制器能做一个好人
really you want your controller to become a good citizen:
不再占用资源
Stop using resources.
你不在屏幕上了 停止吧 好吗
You’re not on screen, stop it. Okay?
当你再回到屏幕上的时候 会再次调用 viewWillAppear
You’ll get viewWillAppear when you go back
可以再同步回去
and you can sync back up to the world.
但是当你从屏幕上消失后 就要保持低调
But after you disappear, you kind of want to lay low, right,
少占用内存空间和 CPU 性能
in terms of memory usage and certainly CPU –
你并不想再继续使用 CPU
you don’t want to be using CPU.
这里很适合停止某项操作
So this is a good place to do stuff like that
也许还要记住当前状态
and to maybe remember state
以便之后在 viewWillAppear 中恢复等等
that you’re going to restore in viewWillAppear again, whatever.
都是你们可能想要做的事情
Kind of what you might think.
这些方法都有 did 已完成的版本
There’s also did versions of these.
viewDidAppear 和 viewDidDisappear
viewDidAppear and viewDidDisappear.
和大家可能想到的作用一样
And that happens exactly what you might think, right?
viewDidAppear 会在你出现在屏幕上后被调用
ViewDidAppear gets called after you’re now on screen.
你一出现在屏幕上 然后这个方法就被调用了
Okay? You just appeared and you just got called, okay?
而 viewDidDisappear 是在你从屏幕上消失后被调用
Same thing, viewDidDisappear — you just disappeared.
现在 我们来讲讲几何方面的内容
Okay. Now, let’s talk about geometry.
我把这部分单独放在了一张幻灯片上
Okay. I put this off to this slide.
关于几何部分 在 iOS6 中引入了两个很棒的方法
Your geometry, in iOS 6 they introduced these really cool two methods
viewWillLayoutSubviews 和 viewDidLayoutSubviews
viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews.
就是在这里面添加几何相关的代码
This is where to put geometry-related code.
在 iOS7 想要布局你的子视图 布局视图之前
So viewWillLayoutSubviews is called just before
viewWillLayoutSubviews 被调用
iOS 7 tries to layout your subviews, tries to layout your view.
你可能刚刚从竖屏
Okay? So your geometry just changed
换到了横屏
maybe from portrait to landscape.
而在 iOS7 中 有很多自动操作内容 叫做自动布局
And there’s a lot of automated stuff in iOS 7 called autolayout
会尝试将所有元素移动至合适位置
that will try and move everything around to fit.
并不总能实现 但它会尝试
Now, it can’t always do it but it tries.
在此之前 系统会调用 viewWillLayoutSubviews
Okay? So viewWillLayoutSubviews is called before that.
而 viewDidLayoutSubviews 会在完成之后被调用
And viewDidLayoutSubviews is called after it’s done that,
完成尝试之后
after it’s made that attempt. Okay?
如果某些东西被手动移动了
Now, if there’s some things that have been moved manually,
你需要手动移动它们
you have to move them by hand,
在自动布局规则中
okay, that there’s just no way to express
不能清楚表达要移动到哪里
in the automatic layout rules where things go,
那么最适合执行它的地方
then best place to do it
也许就是 viewDidLayoutSubviews 中了
is probably in viewDidLayoutSubviews, okay,
因为系统已经将各元素摆出来
because the system’s already laid things out.
现在你可以移动调整
Now you can move around the last few pieces
最后几个需要布局的元素
that need to be laid out.
但是按钮这类对象
But things like buttons, you know,
比如添加和去除轮廓按钮
like that outline and unoutline button,
很容易实现布局
it’s really easy to make it
当你旋转至横屏时 它们就会移动到下角
so that when you rotate to landscape they move down to the corners.
这应该是我们想要的效果
Okay? That’s what you probably want there.
文本视图也是一样的
Same thing, the text view,
当转为横屏时
pretty easy to make it widen out and get shorter
可以轻松地加宽变短
when it goes to landscape.
但是像 Matchismo 那样 你有很多卡牌
Okay? But like in Matchismo, you got all those cards.
当旋转屏幕时 你希望使用某种逻辑来判断出
When you turn it, you might want to use some logic to figure out:
竖屏转为横屏时
Where are you going to lay the cards out
这些卡牌要放在哪里
in a landscape orientation versus portrait?
大家下周要实现这个功能
Okay? And you’re going to have to do that next week.
不是这周的内容
Okay? Not this week.
我想再讲一些关于自动旋转的内容
So I want to talk a little more about autorotation.
也就是 当你旋转手机时
So this is the thing where you turn the phone
几何布局会自动变化
and your geometry automatically gets changed.
这种自动调整至新的几何布局的功能
That automatic change to the new geometry only happens
只会在这些条件为真时会发生
if these conditions are true.
视图控制器的 shouldAutorotate 方法是否返回 YES
Your view controller has to return yes from shouldAutorotate,
这是默认值
which is the default.
你的视图控制器需要从 supportedInterfaceOrientations
Your view controller has to return that new orientation
返回那个新方向
from supportedInterfaceOrientations.
这是一个方法 它返回一个数字
That is a method that returns an e num
代表横屏 竖屏和倒立竖屏方向
with landscape and portrait, portrait upside down in there.
你需要声明支持多个旋转方向
So you have to say that you support the various rotations.
我相信默认是支持全部旋转方向的
I believe by default it supports all rotations.
你的整个应用
And your application as a whole
需要支持那个新方向
has to say that it supports that new orientation.
这个设置…
Okay? And that is set –
还记得我们第一次创建应用 运行它的时候吗
remember when we first built our application and it ran?
当时出现了应用的各种设置
There was, like, all these kind the settings for our app
我挥了挥手说
that I just waved my hand and said,
我们后面再讲
”We’ll look at this later”?
里面有一个设置
Well, one of the settings in there
是应用支持设备的哪个方向
is which orientations of a device –
竖屏 横屏 倒立竖屏
portrait, landscape, portrait upside down — do you support?
你需要在那里选中应用支持的方向
Okay? So you have to click on the ones that you support.
如果这些都做了 那么当设备旋转时
And if you do all these things, then when the device rotates,
你的视图的边界就会自动变化
your bounds of your view will automatically be changed
你会得到 viewWillLayoutSubviews
and you’ll get the whole viewWillLayoutSubviews,
viewDidLayoutSubviews 自动旋转
viewDidLayoutSubviews, autorotate,
自动布局 都会实现
autolayout, all that happening.
也会调用其他方法
Okay? There are also methods that get called.
我把它们设成了灰色
I put them in gray here
因为我们不会讲解这些方法
because we’re not really going to look at them.
很少会用到它们
They’re rarely needed.
自动布局和 viewDidLayoutSubviews
Autolayout and viewDidLayoutSubviews
通常包含了所有需要的内容
are usually going to cover everything you need.
但是如果你想要改变旋转动画等内容
But if you wanted to get involved in the animation
也都是可以的
of the rotation and all that, it’s all possible.
但我们就不详细讲了
But we’re not really looking at that.
在内存不足情况下
Okay. In low-memory situations,
你的视图控制器会收到这条消息
you’re going to get this message to your view controller
叫做 didReceiveMemoryWarning
called “didReceiveMemoryWarning.”
内存不足并不代表
Okay? And low memory doesn’t necessarily mean
你的应用占用了很大的内存空间
your app is using a lot of memory;
也许只是手机上运行的所有应用
it just might be all apps on the phone combined
一块占用了很大的内存
are using a lot of the memory
需要释放一些空间
and it needs some of it back.
它也许向很多应用都发送了这个消息
So it might be sending this to lots of applications.
是否生成这个警告
It’s completely up to the system
完全由系统决定
to decide whether it wants to generate this warning.
当你收到警告后 唯一的责任就是
And your only responsibility when you get this thing
试着释放内存
is to try and free up memory.
也就是堆中的内容
Okay? That means in the heap.
也就是将强指针设为 nil
And that means setting strong pointers you have to nil.
如果你展示一幅图像
Okay? Now, if you display an image, okay,
如果你的 MVC 展示一幅图像 会占据很大内存
if your MVC displays an image, that’s big memory.
图像需要很多内存空间
Images are a lot of memory.
或者播放一段声音 也需要很多内存
Okay? Or it plays a sound — that’s a lot of memory.
但是如果你的视图控制器
But if your thing is on screen,
正在屏幕上显示
if your view controller is on screen,
就不能释放那张图像
you can’t throw that image out.
它需要显示在屏幕上
It needs to be on screen.
所以如果你在屏幕上
So there’s really not much you can do
收到了 didReceiveMemoryWarning 你其实没有太多可做的
when you get didReceiveMemoryWarning if you’re on screen.
但是如果你有一张可选图像之类的
Now, however, if you have an alternate image
现在不在屏幕上
or something that’s not on screen right now,
只要你可以重新创建它 就可以先将它设为 nil
you could set that to nil as long as you can recreate it, okay –
不管你是从文件系统中重新创建
either recreate it by getting it from the file system,
还是网络调用 重新下载一幅
even making a network call to download an image
只要图像不是立刻需要就可以
as long as the image doesn’t need to be instantly available.
这是处理内存警告的一个例子
But that’s an example of how you could respond to this.
尤其是当你不在屏幕上时 你可以响应这个警告
Especially if you’re off screen you could respond to this,
尽管我认为 当你离开屏幕时
although my argument is when you go off screen
会调用 viewDidDisappear 和 viewWillDisappear
and you get viewDidDisappear or viewWillDisappear,
不管怎样 你都应该释放它
you should free up that stuff anyway.
调用 viewWillAppear 时再重新获取
Okay? And get it back when you do viewWillAppear.
因为你不希望自己成为内存占用大户
Because you don’t want to be a memory pig.
成为内存占用大户会怎么样呢
Okay? Now what does it matter to be a memory pig?
我们为什么要在意
Why do we care?
有两点原因
Well, couple of things.
首先 只针对内存大户
Okay. First of all, by the way, only things that use a lot of memory
比如图像 视频 声音
are things like images, video, sound –
这些内容需要很大内存
those can use a lot of memory.
像内含五项内容的词典这类小东西
Small things like little dictionaries with five things in them,
几乎不占什么内存
that’s using virtually no memory.
不用浪费时间释放它们
I wouldn’t even waste your time freeing those up.
那样只会让你的代码变得复杂
Okay? That’s just going to make your code complex for nothing.
所以在说释放内存问题时
So we’re talking about good-sized things, okay,
我们说的是大型内容
when we say “Free things up.”
但是这里我们为什么要乖乖释放内存呢
But anyway, why do we want to be a good citizen here?
如果 iOS 认为你大量侵占了内存
Well, iOS has the right to kill your app
它是可以终止你的应用的
if it thinks you’re being a memory hog.
如果系统内存不足
Okay? If there’s not enough memory on the system
而你的应用恰好占用了很多内存
and your app happens to be using a lot of memory,
它就可以过来说 杀掉它
it can just come along and say, “Bam-o, killing that baby.”
它完全可以这样做
It’s perfectly within its rights.
如果你合理使用内存 它绝不会这样做
If you’re a good memory citizen, it’s never going to do that.
但是想要做一个好的内存使用者
Okay? But being a good memory citizen
你所用的内存不应该超过
means you shouldn’t be using a lot more memory than, you know,
一个 MVC 出现在屏幕上所占的内存
a single MVC that’s on screen right now.
如果应用是运行在 iPad 上的 也许是三到四个 MVC
Or if you’re on the iPad, maybe it’s three or four MVCs,
取决于你的布局
depending on what your layout is.
不管用多少内存 都应该合理使用
You know, however much memory, that would be reasonable to use.
放个视频 没问题 可以的
A video in there, no problem, etc. That’s fine.
但是如果你要在堆中保存 20 个视频
But if you have, like, twenty videos sitting in the heap,
你就是下一个被杀掉的应用
okay, you’re going to be a candidate to get blasted.
另外一点是 你显然希望用户切换应用时
Okay? So the other thing is you obviously want other applications
其他应用
to have as much memory available to them
得到同样多的可用内存
when the user switches back and forth.
如果用户对你的应用所占的内存有一个不好的印象
If you’ve got a reputation as a memory pig like,
每次运行这个应用 其他应用就卡到不行
”Oh, when I run this app, all my other apps slow way down.
真讨厌
Oh, it’s terrible.”
然后他们会到应用商店进行评论
Then on the App Store people are going to say that,
你会得到一个不太好的名声
and you’re going to get a bad reputation,
大家就不想用你的应用了
and people aren’t going to want your application.
这是不要侵占内存的另外一个原因
So that’s another reason not to be a memory pig.
苹果能不能在审核应用时
Can Apple check this kind of stuff
检查你的应用使用了多少内存呢
to see how much memory you use before they approve an app?
是检查的内容吗
Is that a thing?
问题是 苹果公司会不会
So the question is: Does Apple go and check
在批准应用前检查确认
to make sure you’re being a good memory citizen
应用是否合理使用内存
before they approve you?
我不知道
I would say I don’t know.
我不在苹果公司工作
I don’t work for Apple.
我并不知道他们的审核流程
I don’t know what’s going on behind the scenes there
具体是怎样的
in terms of their approval process.
我猜 如果他们运行你的应用后
My guess is if they ran your app
应用立刻占用了大量内存
and it just immediately ballooned up a huge amount of memory,
他们是不会通过审核的
they would not approve it.
这只是我的猜测
That’s just my guess.
如果我是他们 我不会通过的
I mean, I wouldn’t if I were them.
当然了 现在市面上有一些应用
And you know, certainly apps that are out there
以占用大量内存著称
that have a reputation of being big memory pigs,
当这些应用提交新版本等内容时
maybe when you submit your next version or something,
审核人员会说 等等 你们修复内存问题了吗
they’re like, “Wait a second, did you fix that memory thing?”
明白我的意思吗
You know what I’m saying?
这是常识
It’s common sense, common sense.
好的 就是这样
Okay. So that’s that.
我刚才说过 我会讲讲
Okay. Now I told I would talk about
视图控制器的创建
creation of the view controller.
我回来 讲一下这部分内容
And so I’m going back and talking about it here.
我只会简单介绍一下
I’m only going to talk about it briefly
因为它真的不太重要
because it’s really not super important
大多数情况下都会在 viewDidLoad 中进行初始化
because viewDidLoad is where you want most of your initialization.
但是当你的视图控制器创建时
But when your view controller is created,
当它从 storyboard 中取出并加水解冻
when it’s pulled out of that storyboard and unfreeze-dried,
你的 init 方法并没有被调用
your init method is not called.
另外一个初始化方法被调用了
Okay? A different init method is called.
化冻的初始化方法
The unfreeze-drying init method,
它是一个通用的初始化方法机制
which is a generic init method mechanism
我们不会… 也许会讲讲
that we’re not going to — well, we might talk about it
在课程第八周或者第九周的时候
in week eight or nine of this course.
不太重要
Not that important.
但 Xcode 就是用这个方法冻干你的应用的
But that’s what Xcode uses to freeze-dry your apps.
那个初始化方法 你并不会生成它的子类 对吧
So that init — you don’t subclass that init, okay?
它是个初始化方法
Okay, it’s an init;
我甚至不会告诉大家它的名字
I’m not even going to tell you the name of it.
不要生成它的子类
You don’t subclass it.
而当某个元素从 storyboard 中解冻时
Instead, when something gets unfreeze-dried from a storyboard –
任何东西 不只是你的控制器
anything, not just your controller
甚至是按钮之类的东西解冻时
but even, like, a button or anything else comes out of there –
这个方法 awakeFromNib
this method, awakeFromNib –
Nib 是延续以前的名称
Nib is an old historical name;
你可以理解为 awakeFromStoryboard
you could think of it as awake from storyboard –
这个方法会被调用
this gets called.
你可以在这里执行
And you can put in here things
通常会放在初始化方法中的内容
that you might normally put in your init.
虽然这个时候你的输出口还没有设好
Although, again, your outlets are not set at this point.
所以最好放在 viewDidLoad 中
So you’re better off putting stuff in viewDidLoad. Okay?
但是如果因为某些原因
But if there’s some reason
无法将某些操作放到 viewDidLoad 中执行
you can’t put something in viewDidLoad –
我想不出一个好的例子
I can’t even think of a good example why that would be –
这种情况下 你可以放到 awakeFromNib 中
you can put things in awakeFromNib.
如果想要把它变得复杂一点
Now, to make this a little more complicated
也更加正确
but also a little more correct,
可以在代码中
it is possible that your view controller
用 alloc/init 来创建你的视图控制器
could be created in code using alloc init.
允许使用 alloc/init
It is legal for someone to alloc init –
init 并不是视图控制器的指定初始化方法
init is not the designated initializer for view controller
但是 init 可以调用指定初始化方法
but init calls the designated initializer –
所以这样做是可以的
so it is legal for people to do that.
但是这门课上我们不会这样做
Not going to happen in this class.
我们在课上会全部使用 storyboard 来创建
Okay? We’re going to make things out of storyboards for 100% of this class,
所以不用担心
so don’t worry about it.
但是 UIViewController 的指定初始化方法是
But the designated initializer for UIViewController
initWithNibName: bundle:
is initWithNibName colon bundle colon.
同样出于历史原因 这里使用 nib
Okay? Again, historical reasons here with old nib files.
为了保证正确 通常情况下
And so to be correct, we usually like to call
也会在初始化方法中调用 awakeFromNib 中调用的内容
whatever we’re going to call from awakeFromNib also in that init method.
所以你使用这个模板
And so you use this little template
自己创建了一个方法叫 setup 之类的
where you have some method called setup or something,
awakeFromNib 调用它
awakeFromNib calls that,
然后 initWithNibName 中写 self=[super initWithNibName: bundle:]
and then initWithNibName says self super initWithNibName bundle –
因为它是指定初始化方法
because that’s the designated initializer –
然后是 [self setup] return self
self setup return self.
所以如果你要把 awakeFromNib 放在那
Okay? So if you’re going to put awakeFromNib in there,
也要把这三行 initWithNibName 代码一块放进去
go ahead and put this little three-line initWithNibName also in there,
这样才对
just to be correct.
也许在这门课上不用这样做
Okay? Probably not necessary in this class.
你们在课上不需要用到 awakeFromNib
I don’t think you’re going to need awakeFromNib in this class;
viewDidLoad 就足够了
viewDidLoad is what you want.
好了 这是视图控制器生命周期的总结
Okay. So here’s a summary of the view controller lifecycle:
从 storyboard 中进行实例化
It’s instantiated from the storyboard
或者通过调用 alloc/init
or someone could say alloc init, okay;
如果是从 storyboard 中出来的 就会调用 awakeFromNib
awakeFromNib gets called if it came out of a storyboard,
不然就是调用 initWithNibName bundle
otherwise init with nib name with bundle gets called;
如果是从 storyboard 中出来的 设置好输出口
the outlets get set if it comes from a storyboard;
然后 viewDidload 被调用
then viewDidLoad is called;
然后当几何内容都确定之后
then when the geometry is determined,
viewWillLayoutSubviews 和 viewDidLayoutSubviews 被调用
viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews –
这里没有冒号
there should be no colons there;
不知道为什么打错了
I don’t know what, that’s a mistake — get called;
然后 viewWillAppear 被调用
then viewWillAppear gets called;
如果在可见时 几何内容有变化
then if the geometry changes again while it’s visible,
viewWillLayoutSubviews 和 viewDidLayoutSubviews
viewWillLayoutSubviews and viewDidLayoutSubviews
会被再次调用
will get called again.
如果有自动旋转功能
Okay? If there’s autorotation,
就还要加上自动旋转的内容
you also get those autorotation things.
但是不用担心这部分内容
But don’t worry about those
因为通常情况下 你想做的操作
because you’re usually doing what you want to do
都在 viewDidLayoutSubviews 中实现
in viewDidLayoutSubviews.
然后当你的视图控制器从屏幕上离开时
Then when your view controller goes off screen,
会收到 viewWillDisappear 消息
it will get viewWillDisappear.
在此过程中 如果出现内存不足的情况
Okay? If you have a low memory thing at any time going on there,
你会得到这个通知
you’ll get that.
不管是否在屏幕上
That could be while you’re visible or not.
就是这样
And that’s it.
视图控制器生命周期从头到尾的过程就是这样
That’s the view controller lifecycle from start to finish.
好的
Okay? All right.
我们来演示一下
So let’s see a little demo
如何使用视图控制器生命周期
of using the view controller lifecycle.
我要做的是
So what I’m going to do is
记得之前讲过的添加轮廓按钮吧
that outline button we talked about before.
我们让这个按钮上的文字也加上轮廓
Let’s make it so the outline button is itself outlined.
这样是一个很好的 UI
That would be kind of a good UI.
可以更好地表现出这个按钮是做什么的
Okay? So it’s kind of a little more indication of what it does.
问题是 如果我得到这里的这个添加轮廓按钮
Well, the question is: If I have this outline button right here,
我应该何时以怎样的方法为它添加轮廓呢
how and when am I going to outline it?
很遗憾 我不能在 Xcode 里实现
I can’t do it in Xcode unfortunately.
所以我需要用代码来实现
So I need to do it in code.
我想让它一出来就加上轮廓
But I want it to be outlined when the thing first comes up,
而且始终保持这种状态
but — and I want it to always be outlined.
这属于一次性初始化操作
So that’s a one-time initialization thing,
但是这显然要在输出口设置好之后才能发生
but it obviously has to happen after my outlets are set
因为我需要向这个按钮发送消息
because I need to be able to talk to this button.
那么我们先来创建一个对应的输出口
So let’s make an outlet for this.
按住 control 键拖拽到这里
I’m just going to control drag here.
我要叫它 outlineButton
I’m going to call this the “outlineButton,” okay?
我要用到 viewDidLoad
And I’m going to take viewDidLoad.
我要把它移到上面这里
I’m actually going to move it up to the top here.
好了 这是 viewDidLoad
Okay. So there’s viewDidLoad.
我要完全按照注释说的做
And I’m going to do exactly what it says here,
在加载视图后 进行追加设置
do any additional setup after loading the view.
这里应该写 storyboard
This should say typically from a storyboard.
到现在还没有改过来 很好笑
It’s funny that that has not changed.
storyboard 出现在各个 iOS 版本中
I mean, storyboards have been around for — I don’t know –
iOS4 5 6 7 都有
iOS four, five, six, seven, something like that.
到现在还在用 nib
They’re still saying from nib.
但不管怎样 viewDidLoad 就是用来做这个的
But anyway, viewDidLoad is the place to do this.
我们只要设置这个按钮的属性化标题
And all we need to do is set the attributed title of this button
添加轮廓属性
to have the attributes of outline.
我们要怎么做呢
So how are we going to do that?
这里需要大家特别注意
Okay? And this is important for you to pay attention here.
大家都醒着呢 不错
You all look awake, that’s good
周三将要布置的那个作业
because your homework that’s going to be assigned on Wednesday
要用到这部分内容
is going to require this.
你需要设置一个按钮的属性化标题
You’re going to have to set an attributed title of a button.
因为很不巧 作业中的卡牌都是按钮
Okay? Because your cards are buttons unfortunately.
下周之后 它们就不再是按钮了
They won’t be buttons the week after that.
但它们现在是按钮
But they’re buttons right now.
所以你需要用属性化字符串
And so you’re going to need attributed strings
显示我们下周要做的内容
to display what we want to do next week.
所以你们需要设置按钮的属性化标题
And so you’re going to have to set attributed titles to button.
我们来讲一下怎么做
So let’s talk about how we do that.
首先我要写
First thing I’m going to do is
NSMutableAttributedString *title =
I’m going to say NSMutableAttributedString *title equals.
我想得到这个按钮标题的可变属性化字符串形式
So I want to get the title of this button as a mutable attributed string
这样我就能将属性设为轮廓属性
so that I can set the attributes to be the outline attributes
也就是描边宽度等等
that stroke width thing.
所以这里我要写
So the way to do that is I’m going to say
[NSMutableAttributedString alloc]
initWithString: self.outlineButton.currentTitle
initWithString: self dot outline button dot current title.
不管目前标题是什么
So whatever’s on there currently,
现在是 Outline 这个词
which is the word “Outline” right now,
都要使用它
going to use that.
就是这样
And then that’s it.
这里我要示范的操作就是这些了
That’s all I’m going to do there,
为了告诉大家如何实现
just show you how to do this, this way.
其实还可以在这里设置属性 但是…
I could set the attributes there, actually, but –
糟糕 我做对了吗
oops, did I get that right?
现在我得到了标题的可变属性化字符串
Okay. So now I have the title as a mutable attributed string.
我就可以设置这个标题的属性了
So now I can set the attributes in this title.
这个标题现在是一个 NSMutableAttributedString
Okay? Now this title is an NSMutableAttributedString
是我刚刚创建的
that I just created.
它是一个局部变量
It’s a local variable.
它是通过按钮的标题创建的
It’s created with the button’s title,
但它是一个局部变量
but it’s a local variable.
我们继续 设置我们想要的属性
So let’s go ahead and set the attributes we want.
和下面的代码很类似
Okay? Again, it’s very similar to this down here.
那我就直接复制粘贴这段代码
In fact, I’m going to just copy and paste this
稍微改一下
and make one small change.
这里不用 -3 了
Okay. So here, instead of the minus three, okay,
我把它改成 3
I’m going to make it three.
这样就只加轮廓
And that’s going to make this outline thing be outlined
不填充蓝色
with no blue in the middle.
这个按钮的前景色是蓝色
Okay? So the foreground color of this button is blue
或者是默认的黑色
or whatever the default is, black.
但是我这样设置之后
But I’m going to make it
就成为了空心轮廓的样式
so it’s outlined with nothing in the middle.
另外一件事是
The other thing is
我不想让这个按钮是黑色的
I don’t really want this button to be black, okay?
因为按钮都不是黑色的
Because buttons are not black.
按钮是什么颜色的
Now, what color are buttons?
这就引出了另一个有趣的问题
Okay? And this brings up another interesting thing
我们一直还没机会讲
we really haven’t had a chance to talk about,
也就是颜色和色调
which is the tint color.
有些同学已经发现了这个问题
Okay? And some of you have discovered this on your own
因为你们不喜欢 Matchismo 中
because you didn’t like the blue tint
绿色背景配蓝色元素
on the green background in Matchismo.
我对大家对 UI 的直觉
And I applaud you and your UI instincts
和寻找改变方法表示赞赏
to go searching for a way to change that.
正确的更改方法是
And the right way to change it is
有一个全局色调颜色设置
there’s actually a global tint color,
你的整个应用的色调颜色
a tint color for your entire application.
设置方法是打开 storyboard
And you set that by going to your storyboard.
看到这里我的 storyboard 是选中的了吗
See how my storyboard is selected over here?
如果我转到这里
And if I go to the little area here
这是全部属性检查器
that has all my attributes inspector,
如果我点击最左边这项
if I click the left to most one,
也就是文件检查器
which is the file inspector –
它会检查这个 storyboard 文件
it’s inspecting this storyboard file –
可以看到 这里有一个全局色调
you’ll see there’s global tint.
看到了吗
Okay?
全局色调控制你的应用中
So global tint affects all clickable things
全部可点击元素的颜色
in your app everywhere.
所以你可以选择蓝色以外的颜色
Okay? So you could pick a different color than blue.
我们就这样了
And we do that.
另外 像 UIButton 这样的单个元素
The other thing is individual elements like UIButtons,
也有自己的色调颜色
they also have a tint color.
通常情况下 不会单独设置它们
Now, usually you don’t want to set them separately,
尽管很多人发现在模拟器中似乎有一个错误
although a couple people noticed what seems to be a bug in the simulator
如果你设置了全局色调
where if you set the global tint,
在模拟器中会绘制出错误的分段控件
it draws improperly segmented control in the simulator.
我不知道在设备上是否会这样
I haven’t heard back whether it does it on a device.
替代方法就是单独设置色调颜色
But so the workaround was to set the individual tint color.
你可以设置各元素的色调颜色
So you can set tint color individual items
或者设置整个 storyboard 的色调颜色
or you can set it at the storyboard level.
这里我不会设置它
Here what I’m going to do, I’m not going to set it
但我要得到它
but I am going to get it.
我要得到这个色调颜色
I’m going to get the tint color
因为不管这个色调颜色是什么
because whatever this tint color is,
我都要用它进行描边
I want that to be the color that I’m stroking it with,
也就是轮廓颜色
the outline color.
也就是 self.outlineButton.tintColor
So that is going to be self dot outlineButton dot tintColor –
tintColor
tintColor.
明白我在做什么吗
Okay? Understand what I’m doing there?
所以我想让它保持蓝色或其他默认颜色
So I want it stay blue or whatever this color is,
但我只想要描边
but I want it to be outlined only.
范围呢 我需要整个文本范围
And then the range, I need the entire range of text.
也就是说 这里的整个可变字符串标题
In other words, I have this mutable string title here;
我希望全部添加轮廓
I want the entire thing done.
所以我要用到 NSMakeRange
So I’m going to use NSMakeRange,
这是一个 C 结构体
and you’re going to find that for C structs
iOS 中通常会用 NSMakeXX
in iOS there’s usually an NSMake whatever you want
创建 C 结构体
that will make the C struct
让你来指定结构体的成员
by letting you specify the members of the struct.
所以在这个例子中 范围包含一个位置
So in this case a range has a location –
一个起始位置
a starting location –
也就是 0 还有一个长度
which will be zero and it has a length.
长度是这个标题的长度
Okay? Which is going to be title length.
这样就得到了范围
Okay? So that makes a little range.
会将整个范围都设有这些属性
That’s going to set the entire range to have these attributes.
现在我得到了标题的可变字符串形式
Okay? Now I have the title I want as a mutable string,
但我需要再将其设置为按钮标题
but I need to set this back on the button.
因为这里 只有在它是局部变量的情况下
Okay? Because I’ve only can done this
我才能这样做
as a local variable right here.
因为按钮中没有像文本视图中那样的可变属性化字符串
Because there’s no mutable attributed string in button
可以让你随意修改
like there is in text view that you can just modify;
你必须得到它 做一个可变版本
you have to get it, make a mutable version, you know,
编辑后再设置回去
edit it, and then set it back.
我们这样实现 self.outlineButton
And the way we do that is self dot outlineButton
setAttributedTitle: title forState: UIControlStateNormal
setAttributedTitle: title forState: UIControlStateNormal.
就像是在设置标题 但是设置的是属性化标题
Okay? So it’s just like set title but set attributed title.
我们看看是否管用
Okay? So let’s see if that works.
好的 成功了
Okay. And it did.
可以看到 Outline 现在是有轮廓的
So you can see the outline right there is outlined.
轮廓效果不是很明显
It’s not awesomely outlined,
很难看出来
or it’s kind of hard to see that it’s outlined.
我也许可以回到这里再设置一下 比如说
I might want to go back to here and set this, for example –
这个添加轮廓按钮 不再是系统字体了
this outline button — instead of being just the system font,
也许我想让它变成加粗的系统字体
maybe I want this to be bold system font, which — oops –
这样看起来轮廓效果更好
which will make it outline a little better.
所以我们转到这里 检查它
So let’s go to here, inspect it,
字体这一栏不再选择系统字体了
and in the font here instead of using the system font,
我要选择加粗系统字体
I’m going to use the bold system font.
现在再运行
And now when I ran,
它会看起来更粗一点
it will look a little bolder.
这样好点了
So it’s a little better,
更容易看清轮廓
a little easier to see the outline.
它依旧是一个按钮
Okay? And it’s still a button.
如果我点击它 它还是会为文本添加轮廓
If I click it, it still outlines the text.
好的
Okay? All right.
这里我想展示的内容就是这些
That’s all I wanted to show you there.
我要再演示一个视图控制器生命周期的内容
I’m going to show you another view controller lifecycle thing.
但我们先来再讲几张幻灯片
But first, let’s do a couple of slides.
我想给大家介绍另外一个东西
I want to show you one other thing,
我说过我会讲到的
which I promised I would show,
也就是广播站机制
which is this radio station thing.
对象间的通信
So the way of communicating between objects
以一种盲目结构进行
in a blind structured way,
也就是 MVC 的广播站机制
which we refer to as this radio station thing from MVC
在 iOS7 中叫做通知
is called “Notifications” in iOS 7.
今天我们只会介绍
And we’re only going to talk today
如何收听广播
about how to tune into the radio station;
不会介绍如何进行广播
we’re not going to talk about how to broadcast on the radio station.
而且今天
And in specific today,
我们只会介绍收听系统广播
we’re only going to tune into a system radio station,
一种 iOS7 的广播
an iOS 7 radio station.
在后面的课程中 当我们讲到
Later in the course when we start talking about
使用数据库构建更复杂模型的时候
building more sophisticated models using databases,
我们才会介绍如何使用广播站机制
then we’ll really start using the radio stations
来监听模型的变化
to hear about changes in the model. Okay?
但是今天我们只要监听系统的变化
But today we’re just going to hear about change in the system
因为我只是希望大家能有一个印象
because I just want you to get an idea
知道接收端的广播站机制是怎样的
of what that radio station looks like on the receiving end.
真的非常简单
And it’s really, really easy.
有一个类叫做 NSNotificationCenter
There is a class called NSNotificationCenter.
这个类有一个方法叫做 defaultCenter
It has a class method called defaultCenter.
返回一个类似于 NSUserDefault 的共享实例
That returns a shared instance kind of like NSUserDefault,
类似于标准的 UserDefault
standard UserDefault did — a shared instance
你就用这个对象来收听广播
That’s the object you use to tune into radio stations.
方法是向它发送这个消息
And you do it by sending it this message:
addObserver selector name object
addObserver selector name object.
第一个参数 observer 代表
The first argument observer, that is,
想要收听广播的对象
the object that wants to listen to the radio station.
所以在你的控制器中
So in your controller –
因为控制器是最常见的广播收听者
because controllers are the most common radio station listeners –
这个参数可能就是 self
this would probably just be self.
addObserver: self
这是你的控制器代码中的内容
This is somewhere in your controller code.
selector 是 observer 中的方法
Selector is the method inside of the observer
当广播上出现内容时会调用它
that you want to be called when something appears on the radio station.
当进行广播时
Some broadcast happens.
name 是广播站的名称
Okay? Name is the name of the radio station.
你想要收听哪个广播站
Okay? Which radio station you want to listen to.
而这里的 sender object: sender
And sender there — object sender –
代表你是否只想收听某个特定对象
that’s if you only want to listen to radio station broadcasts
发出的广播
that come from a certain other object.
通常这里都会写 nil
Often you pass nil here,
表示频率上任何广播
which means if anyone broadcasts on that frequency,
我都想收听
I want to hear it.
但可能会在某种特定情况下
Okay? But it is possible in certain cases to say,
我只对某个对象
”I’m only interested in changes
发出的广播内容变化感兴趣
in the radio station generated by this object.”
这种情况下 这里就要加上 sender
So that’s the sender there that you would put.
这里将要被调用的方法
Okay? The method that’s going to get invoked here –
如果出现广播时将要调用的方法
method to invoke if something happens –
总有一个参数 是一个 NSNotification
always has one argument, which is an NSNotification.
NSNotification 有三个属性
Inside an NSNotification there are three properties:
一是 name 广播站的名称
One is name, that’s the name of the radio station –
和上面传递的参数是一样的
same thing that was passed above;
object 就是向你发送这个通知的对象
object, okay, that’s the object sending you this notification,
就是上面的 sender
so that would be the sender anything above;
然后是 userInfo 是一个 ID
and then userInfo, which is an ID.
想要知道它是什么 你需要知道
And to know what that is, you have to know
进行广播的那个人
what the person who broadcasts on the radio station
会提供什么
says they will provide there.
明白了吗
Does that make sense?
所以这个 userInfo 是取决于广播站的
So that userInfo is radio station-dependent.
但是如果你知道广播站的名称
But if you know the name of the radio station,
你也许就可以去文档中查找
you probably are looking in the documentation to find it,
文档也许会告诉你
it probably says there,
你要得到的用户信息是 X Y 或者 Z
”Oh, and the user info you’ll get is X, Y, or Z.”
但它是一个 ID
But it’s an ID.
所以你要知道它是什么
So you have to know what it is.
你也许需要对它执行 isKindOfClass
You’re probably going to do is kind of class on it,
或者 respondsToSelector 等来使用它
or response to selector, or something like that to use it.
很多情况下它都是 nil
A lot of times that’s nil
因为我们真正关注的是
because all we’re really interested in
是否有广播
is whether there was a broadcast,
而不是是否广播了某个特定信息
not any particular information that was broadcast.
有问题吗
Question?
sender 是应用中全局变量
About sender is that global over just your app,
还是整个系统中的全局变量
or global over the whole system?
这些东西
All this stuff –
问题是 sender 是整个系统的全局变量
the question is: Is the sender there global to the whole system
还是只是应用中的呢
or just inside your app?
通常情况下 所有关于通知的内容
Always everything about notifications
都是应用内的
inside your app, okay?
因为堆中对象的空间
Because the space of objects in the heap
是在应用内的
is only inside your app.
你不能查看其他应用的数据
You can’t see in other apps.
出于安全考虑
You know, they have their own segregated
各个应用都被分隔在单独的空间
for security reasons space.
所以如果你在这里得到一条系统消息
So if you’re getting a message here from the system,
这里就要是 nil 对吧
this is going to be nil, okay?
sender 会是 nil
The sender’s going to be nil.
什么问题 一样的问题吗
Question? That was your question?
好的
All right.
另外一点需要理解的是
So another thing to understand is
当你结束收听 关掉广播
when you’re done listening, tune out.
将广播关掉
Turn your radio off. Okay?
方法是 向通知中心发送一条消息
And you do that by sending a message
告诉它 removeObserver
to the notification center saying “removeObserver.”
你可以将自己作为观察者
And you can remove yourself as an observer
从全部广播站中移除 就是上面这行代码
of all radio stations with the first one
或者将自己从某个广播站的收听列表中移除
or you can just remove yourself from listening to certain radio stations,
通过指定广播站的名称
okay, by specifying the name of the radio station
和你不想再收听的 sender 来实现
and who the sender is you don’t want to listen to anymore.
做这步很重要
Okay? It’s important to do this because,
因为不幸的是 通知中心始终用一个指针指向你
unfortunately, the notification center keeps a pointer to you
叫做 Unsafe retained 不安全保留
that is called “Unsafe retained.”
指针类型不是强或弱 而是不安全保留类型
So it’s not strong or weak; it’s unsafe retained.
不安全保留类型指的是
And what unsafe retained means is that
如果没有调用它就离开了堆
if you go out of the heap without calling this first,
通知中心可能会试着给你发送一个通知
the notification center might try and send you a notification
然后应用就崩溃了
and crash your app.
这就是为什么它是不安全的
That’s why it’s unsafe.
这里为什么要用这些不安全保留指针呢
Now, why are these unsafe retained here?
显然是为了向后兼容
Clearly for backwards compatibility.
这里实际上应该是弱类型
This really should be weak.
如果这是一个指向你的弱指针就太好了
Okay? It would be awesome for this to be a weak pointer to you
因为这时如果你离开堆
because then if you went out of the heap,
通知中心中会设为 nil
it would be set to nil inside the notification center;
绝不会再向你发送任何消息了
it would never try and send you any messages.
将指针自动设为 nil 的这种弱指针机制
But, you know, the whole weak mechanism of setting things to nil automatically,
是 iOS6 和 iOS7 中特有的
that’s an iOS 6, iOS 7 only thing.
如果你的应用是运行于 iOS5 的
So if you had an app that was running on iOS 5,
就不会起作用了
that wouldn’t work.
如果这个应用依赖于这个机制 就会变得很糟糕
And if this depended on that, it would be bad.
我相信最终他们也许会将它们设为弱类型
I’m sure eventually they would probably move these things to weak
直接告诉用户 如果你使用这个 API 性能会降低
and just say, “If you use this API, it’s depreciated;
不能在 iOS5 上运行
you can’t run in iOS 5.”
没准他们会在 iOS8 或者 iOS9 中这样做
I don’t know, maybe they’ll do that in iOS 8 or 9.
我也不知道
I don’t know.
但是这里要注意
But be careful there.
它是不安全保留类型
It’s unsafe retained.
这是你们在这门课程中
It’s the only unsafe retained really
需要注意的唯一一不安全保留类型
you’re probably going to have to worry about in this course.
总之 结束收听广播后
But the bottom line is: Remove yourself
要移除自己
when you’re done listening.
通常情况下 在你的 MVC 离开屏幕后
Now, normally you’re going to remove yourself
就要移除自己
when your MVC goes off screen, okay?
通常只有在 MVC 处于激活状态出现在屏幕上的时候
Because you’re usually only interested in radio station happenings
你才会关注广播消息
when your MVC is active and on screen.
如果出于某些原因 这个没法实现
But if for some reason that doesn’t make sense,
有个方法叫做 dealloc
there is a method called “dealloc.”
所有对象都有这个方法
Every object has this.
会在你的对象将要离开堆前被调用
It gets called just before your object leaves to the heap.
所有属性都为 nil
Okay? All your properties are nil.
几乎已经不再是一个对象的时候 调用这个方法
You are barely existing as an object and this gets called.
是最后的关联
Okay? It’s that last hook.
所以也可以在这里解决不安全保留指针的问题
And so you can fix unsafe retained pointers to you there.
我不建议使用 dealloc
Okay? I don’t recommend using dealloc.
可以肯定的是 在这门课中 不要为了其他原因使用它
Don’t use it for anything else, that’s for sure in this class.
我建议使用移除 更合理
I suggest removing, it would make sense.
有问题吗
Question?
如果你将自己从观察者中移除
How do you remove yourself as an observer
但你却不是一个观察者呢
and you’re not an observer on anything?
好问题
Great question.
问题是 如果我调用了 removeObserver
So the question is: What if I call removeObserver
但我却没有观察任何对象会怎样
and I’m not observing anything?
没问题
No problem.
不会发生不好的事情
Nothing bad will happen.
那么你可以直接放到 dealloc 中
So you could just throw that in dealloc.
可以的
You could.
你可以这样做
并不是很好的编程方法
It wouldn’t be very nice programming.
不是很好看
It’s kind of not very pretty,
但是为了安全 你可以直接放到 dealloc 中
but you could just throw that in your dealloc to be safe.
但是更好的方法你们知道的
But better to, you know — okay.
接下来是一个示例
So here’s an example.
这个示例我会快速演示一下
This is an example I’m going to demo real quick here,
是关于文本大小的
which is text size.
在 iOS7 之前的版本中都没有这个功能
So in iOS 7 — not in any iOS before that, but in iOS 7 –
但在 iOS7 中 如果你使用了推荐字体
if you use preferred fonts, then the user can actually
用户可以进入设置界面改变字体大小
go into settings and change the size of their font.
如果他们像我一样
So if they’re like me
随着年龄的增长 手机要拿得更远一些才能看清
and the phone has to be held farther and farther away as the years go by,
你就可以将字号调大
you can set the text size up
然后把手机拿近一点
and move that phone back in a little bit.
文本大小就可以实现这样的功能
So that’s what this text size thing allows you to do.
如果文本大小发生了变化
Well, if that text size font change happens,
你需要收到通知 然后改变字体
you have to get notified so that you can change the fonts,
变为用户设置的新的推荐字体 对吧
use the new preferred font that the user set, okay?
获取这个通知的方法是
So you get that notification
在广播站通知中心登记
by signing up in the default center for the radio station
使用 UIContentSizeCategoryDidChangeNotification
called UIContentSizeCategoryDidChangeNotification.
你可以认为它可以是
Okay? You could argue it could be something
推荐字体改变之类的东西
like preferred fonts change.
但它不是
But it’s not.
而是 UIContentSizeCategoryDidChangeNotification
UIContentSizeCategoryDidChangeNotification, okay?
登记进去之后
You sign up for that,
无论何时这些字体改变了大小 你的方法
and whenever those fonts change size, your method –
我这里叫做 preferredFontSizeChange
”preferredFontSizeChange” is what I called mine –
会被调用
will get called. Okay?
我们来看一下如何将其添加到 Attributor 中
So let’s take a look at how we would add that to Attributor
因为 Attributor 使用了推荐字体
because Attributor uses preferred fonts.
如果我们改变了字体大小
And if we change the font size,
我们希望正文和标题
we want the body and the headline
都变成更大或更小的字体
both to change to the bigger or smaller font.
我们来做一下
So let’s do that.
回到 Xcode
I’m going to go back here to Xcode.
好了
So here we are.
想要实现这个功能
The other thing we’re going to need to make this work
我们还需要视图控制器生命周期
is the view controller lifecycle.
只有在我们是在屏幕上的 MVC 的情况下
Okay? Because we’re only interested in those font changes
才会关注这些字体的变化
if we’re the MVC that’s on screen,
我们一直都在
which we always are,
当然是这样 因为我们只有这一个 MVC
of course, because we only have this one MVC.
但很快 我们会添加其他 MVC
But soon we will have other MVCs
就不会始终都在屏幕上了
and we won’t always be on screen.
我们用视图控制器生命周期方法 viewWillAppear
So let’s use the view controller lifecycle method viewWillAppear.
当一个视图将要出现时
Okay? So when a view will appear –
注意这里始终都要加上 super
notice I’m always going to do super there.
你可以在具体操作之前或之后调用 super
You can call super before or after you do your work.
取决于你想要什么
It kind of depends on what you want.
你想让你的超类
Do you want your super class to get a chance
在操作之前还是之后被调用
after you’ve done what you want to do or before?
通常是无所谓的
Usually it doesn’t matter too much.
我并不知道那个 UIViewController
I don’t know that UIViewController
是否真的在这些超类中执行了操作
actually does things in these supers,
但是依旧要给它们机会 对吧
but you always want to give them the opportunity, okay?
这只是视图控制器生命周期的一部分
It’s just part of the view controller lifecycle.
当视图出现时
So when the view appears,
我想在通知中心中登记
I just want to sign up with the notification center
这样我才能接收到这些消息
so that I can receive these messages.
所以这里我要写
So I’m going to say is
[NSNotificationCenter defaultCenter] addObserver: self
[NSNotificationCenter defaultCenter] addObserver: self,
明白吧
Okay?
我想让这些消息发送给我
I want these messages sent to myself.
而 selector 要记得用 @selector
The selector, remember we have to say “at sign selector”
来指定内容
when we want to specify a thing.
我要叫它 preferredFontsChanged
I’m going to call it “preferredFontsChanged.”
name 是 UIContentSizeCategoryDidChangeNotification
Okay? Name is UIContentSizeCategory –
太好了 可以直接补全
lucky, I get to tab through that one.
object 是 nil
Okay? And the object is nil.
也就是说 如果有人发送了消息
In other words, if anybody sends that,
我就要改变我的推荐字体
I’m going to change my preferred fonts.
注意这里有一个警告
Okay? Notice there’s a warning here,
因为我没有实现这个
that’s because I don’t implement this.
我觉得这是 iOS7 中的新内容
I believe that’s new in iOS 7.
我不记得以前见过
I don’t remember seeing that before.
好的 谢谢
Okay. Thank you.
这里太多 r 了
Too many Rs.
(void)preferred
Okay. View — void here preferred.
糟糕 多了个 f
Oops. Two Fs now.
preferredFontsChanged 参数为 NSNotification
Okay, preferredFontsChanged takes an NSNotification star,
然后是 notification
okay, notification,
我不会用它
I’m not going to use that
因为基本上它只是一个布尔值
because it’s just basically Boolean.
实际上我要调用另外一个方法
And I’m actually going to call another method.
我要调用 usePreferredFonts
I’m going to call usePreferredFonts,
你们马上就能明白这里为什么要这么做
and you’re going to see why here in a second.
这样设置好之后 只要我的视图出现
Okay? So that set it up so that anytime my view appears,
我就会得到这个 usePreferredFonts
I’m going to get this usePreferredFonts sent to me –
会发送给我
preferred fonts sent.
在这里 我要让我的文本视图和标题
And in here I have to make my text view
使用新的推荐字体
and my headline use the new preferred fonts.
非常简单
And that’s really, really easy to do.
self.body.font=[UIFont preferredFontForTextStyle: UIFontTextStyle
self.body.font equals UIFont preferredFontForTextStyle UIFontTextStyle –
这是正文 所以这里我要写 Body
this is the body, so I’m going to do Body.
我正好可以借此机会介绍一下
So this has allowed me an excuse to show you
如何使用代码设置推荐字体
how to set these preferred fonts in code
而不是在 Xcode 中进行设置
instead of setting them in Xcode.
就是这么简单
This is how easy it is.
现在我在设置 UITextView 的字体
Okay? Now I’m setting the font of the UITextView.
所以如果我之前设置了加粗或者斜体
So if I had any bolds or italics,
这里设置之后就不再有这些效果了
unfortunately this would blast them.
显然 我需要逐一查看各个属性
So obviously, I would need to iterate through all the attributes
查看字体
and look at the font,
得到符号特征
get the symbolic traits,
像我之前讲过的那样 应用它们
apply them like I talked about earlier.
接下来 我们对标题进行同样的操作
And then let’s do the same thing for the headline,
但是它的字体要是标题推荐字体
but its font wants to be the preferred font for headline,
也就是这个
which is this one.
就是这样
Okay? So that’s that.
还有一点要考虑的是 我需要停止收听
One last thing to consider here is I need to stop listening –
我们在 viewWillDisappear 中执行
we’ll do it in will disappear.
也可以在其他方法中实现 但是这里就这样
Could do it in either but — Okay.
当我要消失时 我想要停止收听
When I’m going to disappear I want to stop listening.
这里也是一样的 NSNotificationCenter
And so, again, NSNotificationCenter,
defaultCenter removeObserver
defaultCenter, removeObserver.
有些同学可能会认为这里直接写 self 就行了
Now, some would argue just putting self here,
但我认为这是一个不好的编程方法
but I actually think that’s bad coding because, you know,
如果你在后面又添加了一个新功能
what happens if you add a new feature down the road
你收听了另外一个广播
where you’re listening on a different radio station
而你并不想在视图消失时
that you don’t want to stop listening to
停止收听这个广播
when your view disappears?
这种情况很少见 但也是有可能的
Which is rare, but it’s possible.
所以我认为这里使用这个版本更好
So I actually think it’s better here to use the version of this,
以名称为参数的 removeObserver
which remove observer that takes the name.
我要写 removeObserver: self
So I’m going to say remove yourself
name: UIContentSizeCategoryDidChangeNotification
name is UIContent blah-blah-blah.
object 依旧是 nil
And the object is still nil.
我只从那一个广播站的收听列表中
So I’m only going to remove myself as a listener
将自己移除
from that one radio station.
还有最后一件事
And there’s one last thing to do here,
如果我的视图出现了
which is what happens if my view appears,
我开始监听 它消失了
I start listening, it disappears,
然后改变了文本样式
and then they go change the text style?
然后视图又重新出现了
And then I reappear?
这里我并不会得到通知
Okay? I will not be notified at that point
因为这个文本样式的改变
because the change — the text style change –
发生在我没有收听的时候
happened while I wasn’t listening.
所以你回来继续收听时
So turning your listening back on,
不会收到没有收听时
you don’t get all the messages
发出的那些消息
that happened while you weren’t listening;
你只会收到新消息
you only get new messages.
这也就是我们为什么
So that’s why we probably want
要在 viewWillAppear 中加上 self usePreferredFonts
to say self usePreferredFonts in viewWillAppear.
这也就是为什么我说
This is why I’m talking about where viewWillAppear
在 viewWillAppear 执行同步操作
wants to sync up with the world when it starts.
viewWillAppear 就是这个作用
That’s what viewWillAppear is for.
所以 viewWillAppear 会使用推荐字体
So viewWillAppear is going to use preferred fonts,
不管目前是什么样式
whatever are currently out there.
明白我为什么这样做了吗
Okay? That make sense why I’m doing that?
我们运行一下 看看是否运行正常
So let’s run this and see if it works.
我是在设备上运行的
Now, I’m running this on a device
但是你们在模拟器上运行的时候 也可以打开设置
but on your simulator you can also go to the settings.
这是我的文本 对吧
So here’s my text, right?
我们加点橙色的文本
So let’s even go ahead and put some orange text in there.
现在我要点击 home 键
Okay. Now I’m going to hit the home button
转到设置 就在这里
and I’m going to go to settings, which is right here.
找到下面的通用 我觉得是它
I’m going to go down to general, I believe it is.
是它吗
Is that it?
没错 文本大小
Yeah, text size.
看到这个文本大小了吗
You see text size right there?
可以看到这里有一个滑动条
You can see there’s a slider.
我们把字体放到最大
So let’s make our text really big, okay?
回去 我可以直接回到这里
Go back. I can just go back to here.
它还在模拟器中运行
It’s still running in the simulator.
如果我设置了断点之类的
Okay? So if I had breakpoints and stuff,
还是可以使用的
that would all still work.
可以看到 字体变大了
And now I can see my font is big.
橙色文本还在这里
I kept my orange right there.
可以这样做
You can do this.
我可以为它添加轮廓
I can put an outline on there.
绿色的吧
Green maybe.
绿色轮廓更容易看清楚
Okay, you can see the outline a little better with green.
现在如果我再回到设置页面
And now if I go back again to settings –
将字体大小设为最小 回去
and let’s set this all the way to small and go back.
再回到应用中 可以看到页面变化了
Back to our thing, you can see it updates it.
明白了吗
Okay? So make sense?
大家都明白这里发生了什么吗
Everyone understand what’s going on there?
大家可以看到 在这一部分 我们使用了…
Okay. So there you can see in that part we used –
介绍了如何用代码设置推荐字体
we showed you how to do the preferred fonts in code,
我们还用通知中心收听了广播
and we also used notification center to do the radio station,
还使用了更多视图控制器生命周期方法
and we also used some more of the view controller lifecycle.
涵盖了很多内容
So that was multihit there.
下次课 周三的课上
And so next time — what’s coming up on Wednesday –
我们要继续修改这个应用
we’re going to take this app
添加更多的视图控制器
and we’re going to add some more view controllers to it.
多个视图控制器
So multiple view controllers.
为了完成作业 要特别注意这部分内容
Now, it’s very important to pay attention for that for your assignment
因为这是作业要求中
because that’s the fundamental thing
最基础的内容
we’re asking you to do in the assignment
就是我们周三要讲的内容 创建多 MVC
that’s going to go out on Wednesday is make multiple MVCs –
依旧是 Matchismo
it’s still going to be Matchismo
但是要再增加一个游戏
but you’re going to have to do another game,
都显示在屏幕上
have both on screen,
在屏幕上再显示一项内容
have yet another thing appearing on screen.
最少要有三个 MVC
So you’re going to have at least three
如果想要获得额外加分 需要实现四到五个不同的 MVC
and if you do extra credit, four or five different MVCs.
我们会快速实现多个 MVC
So we’re going to rapidly start going up to multiple MVCs.
会讲到如何通过
We’re going to talk about how to add MVCs
选项卡栏和导航控制器添加 MVC
with the tab bar and also navigation controller.
这是我们会最先学到的两个实现方法
That’s the first two ways we’re going to learn how to do that.
周三还有一项内容需要重点理解
Really important to understand for Wednesday
就是我们将要用到继承
is we’re going to use inheritance
因为你的两个 MVC 会很相似
because two of your MVCs are going to be very similar.
它们都是卡牌游戏
They’re both going to be card games,
但会有一点不同
but they’re going to be a little different.
你要用继承
You’re going to want to use inheritance
来实现二者之间的代码共享
to share a code between them.
周三会开始讲这部分内容
So I’m going to kind of get you started on that on Wednesday.
我会在周三发布第三个作业
And so I’ll be sending out assignment three on Wednesday.
我们本来要在周五演示使用免费的大学开发者计划
Friday we were going to be doing getting your device working
帮助大家在设备上运行应用
with the free university developer program;
但是现在技术不可用
however, that’s not working technically right now.
所以我们移到下周讲
So we’re going to put that off until next week.
下周五 不是这周五
So next Friday — not this week’s Friday,
下周五我们会有一个课外辅导
but next Friday — we’ll be having a section
大家可以来参加
where you can come to the section
我们会帮助大家在设备上运行应用
and we’ll help you get it so it’s working on your device.
更多内容 请访问斯坦福网站
For more, please visit us at stanford.edu.